<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Britains triumphs, or, A brief history of the warres and other state-affairs of Great Britain from the death of the king, to the third year of the government of the Lord Protector.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212596</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475016</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475016</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151118</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2244:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Britains triumphs, or, A brief history of the warres and other state-affairs of Great Britain from the death of the king, to the third year of the government of the Lord Protector.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 184 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Farnham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: Signature A₂ not filmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151118:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Britains Triumphs,</hi> OR, A BRIEF HISTORY OF THE WARRES AND OTHER STATE-AFFAIRS OF Great Britain.</p>
            <p>From the Death of the late KING, to the third year of the Government of the LORD PROTECTOR.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vide quam repentè tempus res mutat humanas,</l>
               <l>Tempora mutantur, nos et mutamur in illis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Farnham,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Popes-head-Alley, neer <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1656.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151118:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151118:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151118:3"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="4+ pages">
                  <desc>〈4… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> that have hapned in this little corner of the Earth for theſe five years laſt paſt; which although per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure they may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed by the courſe and mean allay of this impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht dreſſe; yet in this as in all other Hiſtories, you may find ſome things which may <hi>aut prodeſſe, aut delectare,</hi> either profit or delight thee: One wiſely and truely calls Hiſtory <hi>the faithfull preſerver of things paſt, and the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb facs="tcp:151118:3"/>Prophet of things to come.</hi> Firſt here is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Fall of one of the mightieſt Monarchs in <hi>Europe,</hi> and in him of Monarchy it ſelf, with the ſeverall deſigns and tranſactions that were ſet on foot for the inſtating of his Sonne in the Throne, and the fruitleſſe events thereof. The Conqueſt of <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Reducing oſ <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Revolt of the <hi>Carybe Iſlands,</hi> and the reducing thereof;
<pb facs="tcp:151118:4"/>and of the Iſlands of <hi>Scilly, Jerſey,</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> The Breach between <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces,</hi> and all the memorable Sea-fights that enſued thereupon. The Diſſolution of the (commonly called) ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Parliament. The Calling another Aſſembly or Parliament, with the manner and cauſe of the diſſolution thereof. The Lord Generall made Lord Protector of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb facs="tcp:151118:4"/>of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. the Solemnities uſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, his Reception and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment in the City of <hi>London;</hi> Other things of leſſe moment are inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven and promiſcuouſly mingled up and down the Book, as the nature there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of requireth: And further finding thy kind accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the first Impreſſion, it hath enboldened me to bring down the Story of all the Warres and other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable things of <hi>Britain,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:151118:5"/>to the third year of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector; all which as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and form, I leave to thy Impartiall judgement there to be arraigned, and condemned according to the nature of the offence; and withall I requeſt thee, that with patience, thou wilt paſſe by ſuch faults as have eſcaped the Preſſe, whether verball, ſyllabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, or literall; and ſo fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151118:5"/>
            <head>A COMPENDIOUS NARRATIVE of the moſt Important Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> from the death of the late KING to the third year of the Government of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the <hi>Lord Protector.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS to the external Cauſes of the many evils and miſeries wherewith this Nation hath been afflicted for theſe few years paſt, much might be ſaid, but the chief I have reduc'd to the following Heads.</p>
            <p>The firſt and generall Cauſe was the Sins of the People, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> who (taking a ſurfet of eaſe, plenty and pleaſure) and growing wanton thereby, gazed after novelty (that magneticall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151118:6"/>of the Plebeian rout) and as diſcontented with their preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſought felicity in things they wanted,<note place="margin">Malv. Rom.</note> and were ſtill unſatisfied e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the accompliſhment thereof: whence is occaſioned the hatred of tranquillity, the deſire of motion, the loathing of preſent things, and ſeeking after future.</p>
            <p>Another principal Cauſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> was the lamentable corruptions of the Court, not inferior in vice to the moſt infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Court in <hi>Europe,</hi> not excelling in any thing that might be called ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, but inur'd themſelves to a ſoft and luxurious life, abounding in all manner of voluptuous and effeminate pleaſures, rejecting the more noble dictates of nature and grace, not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieving any one enterprize, that might render them either feared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, or loved at home: but ſtill wanting fuell for the fire of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality, daily invented ſome new and indirect courſes and wayes to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the people; whoſe jealouſies and fears encreaſing with their griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, brought forth a moſt bloudy and inteſtine warre, which ended not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151118:6"/>but in the ſubverſion of Church and State, as then eſtabliſhed, <hi>viz.</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy and Monarchy, the head of both being cut off and the bodies diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited. And though the King was judged to be the Patron of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny innovations and miſcarriages that befell the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, yet I am fully perſwaded they proceeded not from the depravedneſs of his will, but the flexibility of his nature, overwhelm'd by his pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Councell, by which he ſeem'd of a leſſer magnitude then otherwiſe he would have done; yet was he not the worſt although the moſt unfortunate of Princes: and in him ended Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, but not the miſeries of theſe Nations: for after ſome years civil (and yet unnaturall) warre betwixt King and Parliament, they at length terminated in the vanquiſhing of his Armies, the ſurprizall, captivity and death of his perſon, upon a ſcaffold before his Palace of White-Hall, <hi>Jan.</hi> 30th. 1648.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Cauſe which I ſhall mention (though not the leaſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>) was the Pride, Avarice, Ambition and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151118:7"/>ſlothfulneſſe of the Clergy, who not only ſtarv'd their flocks by withhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpirituall food of their ſouls, but alſo tormented their bodies, by exhauſting and ſucking their bodily ſubſtance, inſomuch that the Nation groaned under the burden of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable corruptions, who ſhould have been the examples and leading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cards of piety and ſanctity: yet did the popular fury contribute more to the confuſion of their Hierarchy, then all their Crime put together; nor were they cry'd down with more heat, then afterwards cry'd up, verifying that of the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Quid populi tibi voce places?<note place="margin">Mori Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gr.</note> ſaepe optima caecus</l>
                  <l>Dat vitio, &amp; temerè deteriora probat.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Having now hinted out unto you the Cauſes of our Warres and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions that followed (the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, progreſſe and concluſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to the beheading of the King, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accurately and briefly deſcribed by another hand) I ſhall proceed to that which remains.<note place="margin">May<hi>'s</hi> Brev.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151118:7"/>
            <p>No ſooner was this mighty Prince bereaved of his life and dignity in ſuch ſort as is before related, bnt Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy (the darling of the multitude) was voted chargeable, unneceſſary and uſeleſſe, and the Government was reſolved into that of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>Yet this mutation hapned-not for want of ſuch as by a lineall deſcent, and according to the uſage of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, might pretend a Title to the Crown: for there was a plentifull Iſſue of the late King (both Male and Female) then ſurviving, but from ſome other politicall reaſons beſt known to the then ſwaying Powers, the which added and miniſtred hopes equal to the diſcontents of the people.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Charles</hi> (though eldeſt Son of the late King) inherited little ſave the misfortunes of his Father, and what elſe he could chaulk out with his Sword; yet his greateſt hopes and expectations were from <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the ſeverall factions united, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed him King, and bent their whole ſtrength againſt the Intereſt of the Commonwealth of <hi>England;</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151118:8"/>in ſhort ſpace became ſo formidable, and prevail'd ſo much, that they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt all the ſtrong holds of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (<hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>Londonderry</hi> excepted) both which were ſtraitly beſieged, the former by an Army of 22000. men under the Marq. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by a party of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels: he had likewiſe adjoyning to the territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>England,</hi> the Iſlands of <hi>Scilly, Jerſey,</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> which yet advantaged him no more then by nouriſhing a few ſmall Picaroons to infeſt the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſeas.</p>
            <p>But his affairs in <hi>Ireland</hi> were no ſooner at this height, but they begun as ſuddenly to decline; for there being about 3000 Horſe and Foot ſafely lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at <hi>Dublin</hi> (as the forlorn of a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er body) they were join'd with what other Forces they could then make, all which made not above 9000 at the utmoſt, and commanded by the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and never to be forgotten Coll. <hi>Mich. Jones,</hi> ſallied forth, and not only raiſed the ſiege, but routed the whole Army of the Marqu. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> himſelf hardly eſcaping: about 2000 were ſlain in the place, and in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151118:8"/>purſuit, ſome thouſands were taken Priſoners, as likewiſe all their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Ammunition, Carriages, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, with great ſtore of rich Booty. To adde to their declining eſtate, and help forward the deſtruction of theſe grand confederates, who were thus defeated in the midſt of their mighty Attempts and huge imaginations,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Generall</hi> Cromwell <hi>landed in</hi> Ireland. Aug. <hi>1649.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> Lord Deputy of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> landed at <hi>Dublin</hi> with a powerful Army (about the midſt of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1649.) well accommodated for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of that enterpriſe ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly began. And firſt he laid fiege to <hi>Drogheda,</hi> and in ſmall time (though with ſome difficuly and loſſe) took it by ſtorme; and that he might cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe their obſtinacy, and ſtrike terror into other Garriſons, put to the ſword all that were found in Armes, which were about 3000. Preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which there fell into his hands many other Garriſons, ſome by force, others by ſurrender, <hi>viz. Trim, Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalk,</hi> the <hi>Nury, Wexford, Roſſe, Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donbridge, Kinſale, Paſſagefort,</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more too tedious to relate. In o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſeveral Garriſons
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151118:9"/>of the Enemy were taken, and many conſiderable Parties were routed by others of the Parliaments Chieftains, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord <hi>Broghill,</hi> Sr. <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> Coll. <hi>Venables,</hi> Coll. <hi>Jones,</hi> and others; and though this people have been ſtill on the loſing hand, yet have they held out in Boggs and faſtneſſes even to this day; whereby we ſee, that the vanquiſhing this Nation, was not ſo feaſible as in the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, who made it but a winters work to reduce and ſubject the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereof: a thing ſcarce credible (ſayes our Author) that a Country ſo populous,<note place="margin">Dan. Chro.</note> a Nation of that diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, ſhould not lift up a hand to defend it ſelf! But it ſeems (ſaith he) they were wholly unacquainted with ſuch ſtrange kind of fights, or ſuch weapons; inſomuch that the terror thereof laid them proſtrate to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verrunner; but though the winning of that Nation was accompliſht with ſo much eaſe, yet in the keeping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, was more difficulty and coſt. In ſhort, The Affairs of the Catholick and other their confederate party mouldered and declined more and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151118:9"/>more, to the great grief and diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Royall Party.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Virginia</hi> and the <hi>Carybe</hi> Iflands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Much about this time hapned a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall defection of the Engliſh Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations from their obedience to the Parliament, <hi>viz. Virginia</hi> and the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rybe</hi> Iſlands: where, in the ardency of Popular fury, Liturgy, and Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy were cry'd up, and the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts were ſome ſtigmatized, ſome fined, and ſome baniſhed; which courſes procured them no ſmall trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and loſſe, in the decay of their Trade, and loſs of their ſhips, all Nations being prohibited from tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or traffiquing with them upon pain of forfeiture:<note place="margin">Are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</note> All which were in a few months reduced by a Fleet of ſhips from <hi>England</hi> under Sr. <hi>George Ayſcue,</hi> not being able to ſubſiſt for any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſpace of time without Trade.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh coaſts were likewiſe miſerably infeſted with Pirates from <hi>Scilly, Jerſey, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> but the very Prince of Pirates and Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, was one commonly known by the name of Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> who with the remnant of that Fleet, that (not long before) had revolted from the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151118:10"/>Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout nine tall and warlike Shipps, committed many ſpoyls and depreda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, not only upon the Engliſh coaſts, but in other places likewiſe, whereby the Merchants inccurred no ſmall loſſe.</p>
            <p>Now for the encouraging of Trade and reducing of Pirates, a ſtout and luſty Fleet of Ships, well rigg'd and man'd were ſet forth, which (with Gods bleſſing) ſcour'd the channel and blockt up Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of <hi>Kingſale,</hi> which with the Town being taken by the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> they were forced thence to make all the ſaile they could away, (leaving about three Ships behind) &amp; at length arrived at <hi>Lizbon,</hi> the Impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ial City of the King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> and cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his protection, which was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed them, the which cauſed much trouble, loſſe and detriment to that King; and was the only cauſe of that unhappy difference that fell out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and this Commonwealth, as hereafter will appear.</p>
            <p>Other deſigns were ſet on foot by the Royal party, for the obtaining their ends.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151118:10"/>
            <p>The firſt was tht Commiſſionating of <hi>James Graham</hi> Earle of <hi>Montroſe,</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he raiſing what Forces he could in <hi>Holland</hi> and other parts to invade <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond was the procuring a Treaty between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their King, whereby they might by force or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raud work him into an abſolute So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty over that Nation, making good that known diſtich,
<q>
                  <l>If the Lyons skin will not prevaile,</l>
                  <l>They'l piece it with the Foxes taile.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To give more life to theſe underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, Ambaſſadors were diſpatcht to <hi>Spain, Italy, Denmark, Sweden, Ruſſia, Turky, &amp;c.</hi> in the name of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, which Title (with much confidence) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he aſſumed to himſelf, yet obtained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>either Men nor Monies worth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from any of them, but excuſes, pleas, and complements in abundance; for alas they had rather he ſhould not be at all, than be too great: they that have equall dignity of birth, had
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151118:11"/>rather have no equall than any ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Montroſe</hi> (according to his Maſters Inſtructions,<note place="margin">Montroſe <hi>enters</hi> Scotland,</note> having got together ſome inconſiderable ſupplies of men and monies) at length lands in the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he had not long been, ere he was aſſailed and routed by a party from the Kirk,<note place="margin">Is routed, taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner and executed.</note> and his Perſon brought priſoner in moſt diſgracefull manner to the Caſtle of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> where to fill up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their malice, they hanged him ten yards from the ground, an act ſo barbarous and inhumane, as admits of no compariſon: thus lived and thus dy'd the Mirrour of Manhood and Map of miſery, who for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had been a thorn in the ſide of the Kirk; witneſſe the ſeverall defeats he gave them, and who from ſmall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings accompliſht vaſt enterprizes, whoſe hard fateit was at laſt to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their bloudy hands, <hi>Sic tranſit gloria mundi.</hi> One would have thought this one act of theirs had been of force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to prevent all future overtures between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their declared King: yet as if he had throughly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151118:11"/>learnt that leſſon, <hi>Qui neſcit diſſimulare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſeit regnare,</hi> he took little notice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereof.</p>
            <p>Next <hi>Montroſe</hi> was executed Sir <hi>John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rrey,</hi> Coll. <hi>Spotſwood,</hi> and others that were the chief actors in that underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, by which means they were rid of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dangerous enemy.</p>
            <p>On all this the Engliſh (like caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous ſtatiſts) had a watchfull eye, and on every of thoſe actings, whether o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en or ſecret, that might have any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon them or their affairs: and to the end they might the better ſound the contrivances of their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, they endeavour to ſtrengthen themſelves by forrein Alliance; and accordingly they ſent Dr. <hi>Doriſlaus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Doriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
               </note> a wiſe and knowing man, as publicke Agent, into the united Provinces, whereby to keep a right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and fair correſpondency between the two Republicks: where he had not long been ere he was ſlain by ſix aſſaſſinates that broke into his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at the <hi>Hague</hi> in a diſguiſed habit, by which means they eſcaped unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, notwithſtanding the many en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours (at leaſt pretendedly uſed)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151118:12"/>for their apprehenſion. The author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of this Tragedy were afterwards known to be Engliſh Cavaliers, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented at their declining ſtate, and loſſe of their old Maſter: one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was Coll. <hi>Spotſwood</hi> afore mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who at his death confeſt he was an actor therein. Thus ſtood the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh affairs in reference to their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abroad, while they were in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what worſe plight at home: for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the ſeverall factions that ſprung up during theſe late warres, none was more deſperate then that commonly known by the name of Levellers,<note place="margin">The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers mutiny.</note> who at once ſo wrought with the Souldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that a conſiderable party of Horſe withdrew themſelves from the Army, and gathered together ſuch others of their party as they could convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thinking thereby to force their Lords and Maſters to ſuch things as their immature and unbridled appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions had dictated to them: But by the care and induſtry of Gen. <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt.</note> they are defeated at a place called <hi>Burford</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> and of thoſe that were taken, ſome were made exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, others were caſhiered the Army,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151118:12"/>and the reſt upon their ſubmiſſion were taken into favour.</p>
            <p>Not long after was brought to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all at the <hi>Guildhall London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lilburne <hi>tryed at</hi> Guildhall.</note> the grand Champion, the chiefeſt and only Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot of the action aforeſaid, <hi>viz. John Lilburne,</hi> a man of a reſtleſs and yet invincible ſpirit, that could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be deterr'd with threats, or won with favours, by a ſpecial Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer;</hi> where was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent moſt of the Judges and Juſtices of the ſeverall Courts at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> the Lord Mayor, Sheriffs, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aldermen of <hi>London,</hi> with others of eminent quality. The Indictment with many crimes of a treaſonable nature, as being the Author of ſuch and ſuch Books mentioned therein; which Books were fraught with the moſt ſhamefull revilings, ſcurrilous invectives, and malicious outcries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Governours, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Nation, that the heart of man could invent; calling them Tyrants, Traytors, Conquering Uſurpers, and what not? Now though nothing was more generally beleeved, then that the Books afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151118:13"/>were of his own penning and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing, yet at his triall he made ſuch an excellent,<note place="margin">Is cleared and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed.</note> ſubtle and ſingular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that the Jury brought him in Not guilty, whereupon he had his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe.</p>
            <p>By this time the ſeverall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions that were between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their King, had brought forth a Treaty at <hi>Breda</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The treaty between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their <hi>King</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</note> a Town of ſpeciall note belonging to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> at whoſe coſt and charges it was both continued and concluded: now that part of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement that had the moſt eſpeciall influence on us, was, that they ſhould endeavour to the utmoſt of their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to reinſtate him in his Fathers Throne, inveſt him in his Power and Greatneſſe, and eſtabliſh him in his juſt Rights and Dignities: where we ſhall at preſent leave him to ſee how the affairs of his Adverſaries the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſucceeded.</p>
            <p>The differences that lately broke out between the King of <hi>Portugall</hi> and this Nation, were now widened by acts of open hoſtility; for when the Engliſh perceived, that neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151118:13"/>nor threats would make him force Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> out of his Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and that the often applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and negotiations of the Engliſh Agent Mr. <hi>Charles Vane,</hi> in order thereunto, could availe nothing, but on the contrary prepared what Ships of warre he had to joyn with <hi>Rupert,</hi> and ſo to chaſe the Engliſh from his Coaſts, they ſeiz'd many of his Ships richly laden both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bound: but the King doubting his ſtrength, deſiſted from falling upon the Engliſh Fleet, and ſell to ſeize the eſtates, and ſecure the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Merchants and Factors reſiding in <hi>Liſbon</hi> and other places under his Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>About this time likewiſe the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh ſent an Agent to the King of <hi>Spain, viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Anth. Aſhcam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. <hi>Aſhcam</hi> the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Agent murther'd at <hi>Madrid.</hi>
               </note> a moſt learned and excellently well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht Gentleman, who on the 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1650. landed at <hi>Santa Maria;</hi> where (hearing of many threats a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his perſon) he procured a Guard that conducted him to <hi>Madrid,</hi> where is kept the Court of the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> The firſt night it was his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151118:14"/>hard fortune to lie at an Inne; the next day while with his Interpreter Signior <hi>Riba</hi> he ſate at dinner, ſix divels in the ſhapes of men, knockt at the door, had eaſie acceſſe, and being entred Mr. <hi>Aſhcam</hi> roſe to ſalute them, whereupon the foremoſt ſtabbed him in the head, and his Interpreter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to eſcape was ſtabbed in the belly, both falling down dead in the place. Whence the murtherers fled to the <hi>Venetian</hi> Ambaſſadors houſe, but were denyed entrance: whence they fled to the Sanctuary, were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued and carried to priſon from thence by the Kings ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, one of them only eſcaping. Hereupon aroſe a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and the Church, about the violation of the holy Sanctuary, and thereby infringing the Sacred Rights and Priviledges of the Church, and demanded that the Aſſaſſinates ſhould be delivered again into the Sanctuary. On the other hand the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> by ſundry Meſſages, earneſtly preſt that Juſtice might be ſeverely inflicted upon thoſe execrable offenders, that had perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151118:14"/>ſo horrid and vile an act upon their publick Miniſter. And indeed it was a crime of ſo tranſcendent a nature, that me thinks it ſhould not enter into the heart of any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man to imagine of any expiation for them here, however it may pleaſe God to deale with them hereafter. The Church notwithſtanding pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, ſo farre as to interrupt the courſe of Juſtice, for as much as their puniſhment has been hitherto fuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, though for any thing we hear they are yet in durance.</p>
            <p>Neer this time arrived in <hi>England</hi> the Lord <hi>Gerard Scarph,</hi> as Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner from the States Provinciall of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt Frieſland,</hi> and upon the 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1650. he delivered his Meſſage in Parliament; which though it produced no more then a mutuall deſire of an amicable compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, yet was it very well reſented by the Parliament, that they ſhewed themſelves the leading cards to the reſt of the Provinces at ſuch a time as that.</p>
            <p>Now when as the Treaty at <hi>Breda</hi> was fully ended, and that all their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151118:15"/>Jealouſies and animoſities (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the vaſt diſproportion and notable antipathy that was erewhile between the Royaliſts and Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians) was by this means fully al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed, at leaſt in ſhew. The <hi>Scots</hi> ſeemed to want nothing ſave the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their King, whereby to crown their deſires and confront the Engliſh, in order whereunto he haſts from <hi>Breda</hi> to the <hi>Hague,</hi> from thence to <hi>Scheveling,</hi> where he took ſhipping, and at laſt in deſpight of foul wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Engliſh Kingfiſhers that lay there to intercept him, he landed at the <hi>Spey</hi> in the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he found the greateſt difficulty in aſcending the Throne, and leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed it of any Prince that was ever heard or read of. For upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions he was compeld to trace the ſteps, and follow the dictates of that haughty Clergy, in all their fanatick humours and imperious decrees: who bereaved him firſt of all his old friends, Counſellors and confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, whether of the Clergy or Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, who (to ſay the truth) had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accompanied his Father and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151118:15"/>him in all their dyſaſters and dangers; and had ſhipwrackt their own for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes to carine and repair his, though it may be by this deſertion he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their reſtauration. But now the <hi>Scots</hi> had a King, yet (as though they had none) they did what ſeemed right in their own eyes.</p>
            <p>The firſt and moſt pernicious poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they made him to take, and of hardeſt digeſtion, was the <hi>ſolemne League and Covenant,</hi> that <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> and only ſeminary of bloud and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief in theſe three Nations.</p>
            <p>The next was a declaration of the Kirks own framing and faſhioning; wherein he is taught to <hi>renounce the ſinnes of his Fathers houſe, and of his own, the Idolatry of his Mother, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant adhering to the Cauſe of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Covenant, in the firm eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Church government, as it is laid down in the Directory for publike Worſhip, Confeſſion of Faith and Catechiſm:</hi> This with divers others of the like nature (although with much reluctancy) he alſo ſigned; which it's like, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened his ſpirit, yet bettered not his condition, which was like that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151118:16"/>of a Child under Tutors and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; for there was not an Officer in that Church or Commonwealth, how vile and abject ſoever in place or perſon, but enjoyed more freedome in body and mind then he. Guarded indeed he was, but little regarded; ſo that move he muſt not but in the ſphaere of the Kirk; they were the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> whereby it's apparent that the Government of that Nation was not truly Monarchicall (though they had a King) but Hierarchicall, the confuſion whereof I ſhall now ſet before you.</p>
            <p>The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right well the condition into which their affairs were now reduced (by reaſon of the Agreement that was peeced up between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their King) after a ſerious and ſolemne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> layes down his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd upon General <hi>Cromwell</hi> Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </note> voted that <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> with the Army under his command ſhould march Northwards: who (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome conference had with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) and being prompted by an indiſpoſition of body or mind, laid down his Commiſſion: which was forthwith conferr'd upon <hi>Oliver Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151118:16"/>Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who (in order to this Northern expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) arrived a while after from his victorious archievements in that country, leaving his Son in Law <hi>Henry</hi> as Lord Deputy in his room.</p>
            <p>Accordingly Orders were iſſued forth for the ſpeedy advance of the Army into <hi>Scotland,</hi> who had no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er begun their March, but the <hi>Scots</hi> took the Alarme, and ſent two or three Papers to Sr. <hi>Arthur. Haſterig</hi> then Governour of <hi>Newcastle;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they expoſtulated the Caſe about the ſudden approach of the Engliſh Army, endeavouring thereby to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pede their march, till ſuch time as their deſigns were ripe: alledging (as ſcar-Crowes to fright fools) the Covenant, the large treaty and Union between the two Nations, with other circumſtances of the like nature, as frivolous as they were fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
            <p>The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> then publiſhed likewiſe a Declaration, ſhewing the grounds and reaſons of their Armies advance towards <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> accompanied with another from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151118:17"/>the Generall and officers of the Army,<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Engliſh Army in their march to <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> ſhewing that that which moved them to that great undertaking, was not any reliance upon the arme of fleſh, or being lifted up with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of former ſucceſſes, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of accompliſhing any deſigns of their own that they had forelaid, but the full aſſurance they had that their Cauſe was juſt in the ſight of God: looking at the precedent chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the ſucceſſes that produced them, not as the work of the policy or ſtrength of man, but as the eminent actings of the Providence and Power of God, to bring forth his good will and pleaſure, concerning the things which he hath determined in the world; adding that nothing was ſo predominant with them (next to their duty to God, not to betray a cauſe to which he had ſo much witneſſed) as the love they had to thoſe that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God there, who might poſſibly ſuffer through their own miſtakes, or their diſability to diſtinguiſh in a common calamity: of which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian love they hoped that they gave ſome proof when they were before
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151118:17"/>in <hi>Scotland</hi> with that Army, and were by God made inſtrumentall to break the power of thoſe that oppreſſed the godly Party there; for which (ſay they) their late Engagement to their new King againſt <hi>England</hi> was no good requital, nor their heaping on them the reproach of a Sectarian Army, a Chriſtian dealing: all which (by the grace of God) they could forget and forgive, and did (as they ſay) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of God that the precious might be ſeparated from the vile, beginning and concluding with a moſt ſolemn and dreadful imprecation and appeal; <hi>That to the truth of theſe things the God of Heaven in his great mercy, pardoning their weakneſſes would judge of them when they came to meet the Enemy in the Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Declaration was ſent by the Generall of the Engliſh Forces from their Head-Quarters at <hi>Barwicke</hi> to <hi>Edenburgh</hi> by a Trumpeter, whom they blinded coming and going: what ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect this wrought, the ſequel of the Story will relate.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Barwick</hi> the Army marched to the Lord <hi>Mordingtons</hi> Houſe <hi>July</hi> 22.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151118:18"/>1650. where they lay three dayes: on the 25. they marched to <hi>Copperſpeth,</hi> the 26. to <hi>Dunbar,</hi> where they receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome proviſions from the Ships ſent on purpoſe to attend the motions of the Army; foraſmuch as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Countrey had forſook their habitations, and had left nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind that might accommodate them. The Army thus refreſht at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> marcht thence to <hi>Haddington:</hi> Next day hearing the <hi>Scots</hi> would meet them at <hi>Gladſmore,</hi> they laboured to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the Moor before them, but no conſiderable part appeared, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Major Generall <hi>Lambert</hi> and Collonel <hi>Whalley</hi> men of approved courage with 1400. Horſe were ſent as a Vauntguard to <hi>Muſſleborough</hi> to attempt ſomething upon the Enemy if poſſible; The General with the reſidue of the Army marching in the rear, the Engliſh and Scotch Horſe had ſome encounters, but the Scots would not endure the Shock: that night the Engliſh lay encamped cloſe at <hi>Muſſleborough;</hi> the Enemy was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in four miles of them, intrenched with a Line, flanked from <hi>Edenburgh</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:151118:18"/>to <hi>Leith;</hi> the Guns from <hi>Leith</hi> ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt parts of the Line, ſo that they lay very ſtrong: The Engliſh finding their Enemies were not eaſily to be attempted, lay ſtill all that day being the 29. which proved a ſore day of rain, and greatly diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to them, having nothing to cover them, all which, expecting a ſpeedy engagement, they did cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully undergo it; next day being the 30. the ground very wet, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions being ſcarce, the Engliſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to draw to their Quarters at <hi>Muſſleborough,</hi> to refreſh and revictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; which while they were doing, the <hi>Scots</hi> fell upon their rear, and put them to ſome diſorder. But ſome bodies of the Engliſh Horſe came forthwith to cloſe with them, which produced a hot and gallant skirmiſh, inſomuch that at length the Engliſh charged them ſo home, that they beat them to their very Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Major General <hi>Lambert</hi> in this diſpute was run through the arme with a Launce and wounded in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the body, taken priſoner, but reſcued by Lievtenant <hi>Empſon</hi> of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151118:19"/>the Generals Regiment; ſeveral o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Scots were killed and taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, with ſmall loſſe to the Engliſh: among the reſt there was taken one Lievtenant Collonel, one Major, and ſome Captains, ſome perſons of note were likewiſe ſlain.</p>
            <p>By this means the Engliſh had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to march quietly off to <hi>Muſſleborough,</hi> which they did that night; but ſo wearied for want of ſleep, and tired with the dirtineſſe of the wayes, that they expected the Enemy would make a ſudden infall upon them, which accordingly they did. Between three and four of the Clock next morning, being the 30. of <hi>July,</hi> with fifteen ſelect Troops of Horſe under the Command of Major General <hi>Montgomery,</hi> and Coll. <hi>Straug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han,</hi> who came on with great reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, beat in the Engliſh Guards, and put a Regiment of Horſe into ſome diſorder; but the Engliſh preſently taking the Alarm charged, routed, purſued, and did execution upon them, within a quarter of a mile of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> taking and killing many, as well Officers as Souldiers: the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151118:19"/>Scotch affairs ſucceeding in this ſort, made them forbear ſuch frequent ſallies, and keep within their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments.</p>
            <p>This was the poſture of the Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry affairs in <hi>Scotland,</hi> when to adde to the miſeries of that people, all traffique and commerce was prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted between the two Nations. And ſuch of the <hi>Scots</hi> as had their reſidence in <hi>England,</hi> were commanded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the Land within ten dayes or thereabouts; their Ships (not able to reſiſt, having no Convoy) were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſurprized by the Engliſh, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they were in the road way to ruine: But ſeeing this Moneth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> produced little of action from the Armies there, it will not be amiſs to give a brief account of ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable paſſages as about that time hapned in <hi>England</hi> and the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations.</p>
            <p>At <hi>London</hi> was apprehended, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,<note place="margin">Col. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed at <hi>Towerhill.</hi>
               </note> and executed Collonel <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius Andrews,</hi> who being taken with a Commiſſion from <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and for entring into a conſpiracy to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine the Government of <hi>England,</hi> ſuffered death as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:151118:20"/>
            <p>From the united Provinces came accompt of ſome notable tranſactions, which take as followeth.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (Brother in Law to the <hi>Scots</hi> King, by marrying his Siſter, Daughter to the late King of <hi>England</hi>) aſpiring to a higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Soveraignty over thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces then he or his Predeceſſors ever enjoyed, and being thwarted in ſome of his projects when he was at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> he thereupon was ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, that he reſolved to right him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by ſecuring and putting out the leading men in that Province of <hi>Holland,</hi> for which purpoſe he cauſed all the Deputies thereof (being then at the <hi>Hague</hi>) to aſſemble, which they refuſing, he ſeized moſt of them, thoſe of <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> (whom he chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired) eſcaped only. His next deſign was to have ſurprized the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> by a ſtratagem, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Horſe to ſuch a place, under pretence of conducting his Mother, and ſhipped his Infantry at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trech</hi> in the ordinary Paſſage-boats, to come all night, that they might be there early next morning, and the horſe to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151118:20"/>have their Rendezvouz upon the Heath between <hi>Naerden</hi> and <hi>Amesford</hi> about midnight, and to be at the Ports of the Town at the moment appointed; by which time the foot ſhould have ſeized on the Regulars and the S. <hi>Tunies</hi> Ports, and have opened a paſſage for the Horſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; which deſign (if by a wonderful providence of God in ſending a fierce ſtorm of rain that night, the intended march of the Horſe had not been hindred from coming to the place and time appointed) had in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity taken effect. Nor had the Town known any thing thereof till too late. But the <hi>Hamburgh</hi> Poſt, as he was coming to the Town met with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parties of Horſe, riding to and fro about <hi>Amesford</hi> and the Heath, yet who they were he knew not.</p>
            <p>Hereof the Lords being informed, ſtraightway cauſed the Ports to be ſhut, the Bridges drawn, the Guards ſet, the Ordinance planted, and all war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like preparations to be made; and all this while not knowing their enemies. But they were not long in ſuſpence, for notice was ſoon given, that it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151118:21"/>was <hi>Count William</hi> with his Forces, whoſe deſignments being thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> accoſts the Town with this following Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worſhipfull, Prudent, Diſcreet Sirs, and my very good Friends.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHen I was laſt in the City for the ſervice of the Countrey, I was ſo ſtrangely entertained, that not to be ſubject to the like hereafter, I found it expedient to ſend <hi>Count William</hi> with the Troops following him into your City; and ordered him to keep all things in peace, and quiet there, that I might not be hindred by any all-affected, in ſuch things as yet I have to propound unto you, touching the ſervice of the Countrey, wherein I require your good aſſiſtance; And in conſidence thereof, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending you to the protection of the most High, I remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Hague, <date>
                           <hi>July 29. 1650.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your good Friend,</hi> W. Prince <hi>of</hi> Orange.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151118:21"/>
            <p>This ſtratagem (projected with ſo much ſecrecy and ſubtlety) failing, <hi>Count William</hi> drew off his Forces to ſeverall Poſts, with intent to block up the Town, which being in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of defence, opened their ſluces, and ſet the Land under water round about; and having ſo done, they ſent a Trumpeter to <hi>Count William</hi> to know the reaſon of that ſo ſudden approach, and to deſire him to retreat with his Army, who returned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that he could do nothing till he heard from the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> yet a little after he thought fit to quit his ſtation and retire; yet the Deputies of <hi>Holland</hi> being faſt in the Caſtle of <hi>Lovenſtaine,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had the advantage of make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own conditions which were theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Town of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſhall agree with the other ſix Provinces for continuing the <hi>Militia,</hi> as it is now ſetled for four or five years.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Prince ſhall repair to their City at pleaſure, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon his entry with all reſpect
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151118:22"/>and reverence, as was uſed in times paſt to his predeceſſors, Lievtenants of <hi>Holland,</hi> and have acceſs into their Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhall at the next Aſſembly of the States, uſe their utmoſt endeavours to allay all jealouſies and to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile differences in reference to the late action, and bury all in oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Lords <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Bicher,</hi> ſhall forthwith be removed from Government, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had to their good Names, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and future Security; and if after they have had conference with his Highneſſe the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> he ſhall perſiſt in his opinion touching them, that then they ſhall be rendred uncapable of any Government here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Now though by this means he brought the States under his Lure, and ſubjugated them to his humour; yet this was not the prize he run for, his greateſt hopes and higheſt thoughts being fixed on that inexhauſtible trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure then in the bank at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151118:22"/>with which he might not only have raiſed his declining ſtate, but alſo mount to an abſolute degree of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and Supremacy over that people, and likewiſe might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed much towards the repairing the deſpicable and needy fortunes of his Brother in Law the <hi>Scots King,</hi> to the troubling and diſquieting the peace and tranquillity of theſe three Nations; to all which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God of his goodneſſe to give a check.</p>
            <p>The State of <hi>France</hi> had likewiſe a plentifull ſhare in thoſe incumbrances and common calamities that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to Nations and people by reaſon of forrein and domeſtique broyls; The preſent Cardinall <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarine</hi> was lookt upon as the very efficient cauſe of all their civill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, and the only ey-ſoar of that miſerable people; not much unlike the late blazing Star of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> both Church-men, and yet both Stateſmen, of like intereſt with their King; and of like power over the people, both alike emulated by the Nobility for their Greatneſſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151118:23"/>and of the Commonalty for their grievances; But like Fate hath not befell them; For this Cardinall is neither out of favour with his Prince, nor is he fallen into the hands of the people, for though they have often ſhewed their teeth, it hath never been in their power to bite.</p>
            <p>For during the minority of the preſent King of <hi>France Lewis</hi> the 14. the ſole management of State affairs hath been in the hands of the Queen <hi>Regent,</hi> and her beloved Favourite Cardinall <hi>Mazarine;</hi> at which (after ſome years forbearance) the chief of the Nobility uttered their diſcontents both publickly and privately: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon three of them were arreſted and ſent to priſon, <hi>viz. Lewis de Bourbon</hi> Prince of <hi>Conde, Armant de Bourbon,</hi> Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Longueville;</hi> this adminiſtred freſh oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the people to breath out their diſcontents, thoſe of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> againſt the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon</hi> more eſpecially, but all againſt the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; So that on a ſudden the whole Kingdome was inflamed with civill warres and the appurtenances there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151118:23"/>unto belonging. The principal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of and actors in thoſe tumults, were two famous <hi>Amazones,</hi> the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of <hi>Conde,</hi> and the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Longueville</hi> in behalf of their impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned husbands: Many others of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity appeared alſo in their behalf, and to make themſelves the more formidable, contracted an underhand bargain with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who (greedy to fiſh in ſuch troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) ſupplyed them with conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſummes of money. The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Burdeaux, Paris, Dijon, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe, &amp;c.</hi> countenanced theſe deſigns in oppoſition to the Cardinall and his creatures: So that in ſhort ſpace Armies were raiſed on both ſides, Towns garriſon'd, taken and re-ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, many mens lives loſt, and the Countrey prey'd upon by all parties; The <hi>Spaniard</hi> being not only a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter of, but an actor in theſe por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentous diviſions, for by this means he had the opportunity to march to and fro in that Nation, without any conſiderable oppoſition, taking Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, and waſting the Countrey at his pleaſure.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:151118:24"/>
            <p>Theſe Inſurrections (after many ebbings and flowings, ſtrange Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and tranſmigrations, too tedious here to inſert,) at length produced the liberty of the Princes, the withdrawing the Duke of <hi>Eſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> from <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> the baniſhing the Cardinall with all his kindred and ſi lends from the Court and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: yet was he longer baniſhing then baniſhed; for it was not many moneths ere he returned in great pomp and glory, to the extreame grief of his old malecontents and competitors, the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> and others; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the preſent troubles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with that ſervile people is yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted: where (praying for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance) I ſhall leave them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the more proper ſubject of this diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Engliſh affairs in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moneth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> was nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> done, and little action performed ſave the taking of <hi>Collington</hi> houſe, and <hi>Readhall</hi> by ſtorm, and in it the Lord <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Major <hi>Hamilton</hi> and ſixtie Souldiers, 60. Barrels of Pouder,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151118:24"/>100 Arms, great ſtore of Meal, Malt, Beer, Wine, and other rich plunder: This was done on the 24 of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1650.</p>
            <p>The body of the Engliſh Army re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved forthwith from <hi>Pencland</hi> Hills, to <hi>Collington, Readhall,</hi> and other parts within a mile of the whole Army of the <hi>Scots;</hi> on the 27<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> both Armies marched ſide by ſide, a great bog only betwixt them, which hindred an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, yet the Great Guns plaid on both ſides: <hi>Aug.</hi> 28. the Canon from the Engliſh Camp plaid hard upon the Enemy and greatly annoyed them, all which provoked them not to fight, but ſtill they kept within the protection of the Bog: The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh (being in ſome want of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) drew off to to their old Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at <hi>Pencland</hi> Hills, then with much difficulty to <hi>Muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leborough</hi> to recruit, which done they drew off their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, quitted their Garriſons, and marched to <hi>Haddington;</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on their right wing, fell into their Quarters with a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſolute Party, and were as valiantly repuls'd by a Regiment of Foot commanded by Coll. <hi>Fairfax.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:151118:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1. The <hi>Scots</hi> being ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagiouſly drawn up at the weſt end of the Town, the Engliſh drew Eaſtward into fair and champion ground, fit for both Armies ro en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in: but finding (after ſeverall hours expectation of the enemies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach) that they would not move after them, but to dog them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, they marched towards <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar,</hi> whither the <hi>Scots</hi> moved apace after them, and at a Paſs endeavoured to fall upon the rear, which the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh perceiving fac'd about to fight them: whereupon the <hi>Scots</hi> drew off to the Hills, perceiving their 'advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage lay there, to impede the Engliſh at the Paſſe at <hi>Copperſpeth;</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing effected, they brag'd they had the Engliſh in <hi>Eſſex</hi> his pound, meaning they had them upon the ſame lock the King had the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> at in <hi>Cornwall:</hi> ſo ready are men to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe wonders to themſelves, while they confer but with their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh were indeed invironed with all manner of apparent dangers; their Forces were leſſened, their bodies
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151118:25"/>weakned with Fluxes, their ſtrength waſted with watchings in want of drink; wet and cold weather they were alwayes accompanied with, and much impaired in point of courage, 2000 at leaſt being diſabled for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſervice, were ſent at ſeveral times to <hi>Barwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Generall and his Councell of Officers finding the Army unfit for further delayes,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> defeated at <hi>Dunbar.</hi>
               </note> reſolved next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to break through that their Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelitiſh condition, by falling on the right wing of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and either force a paſſage that way, or periſh in the attempt; and being imbattailed by break of day accordingly, they fell upon the enemy with Horſe and Foot very unanimouſly; who to hinder the Engliſh at a Paſſe, drew up all their Horſe upon their right wing, and valiantly received the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. The Word of the Engliſh was, <hi>The Lord of Hoſts;</hi> and that of the <hi>Scots</hi> was, <hi>The Covenant.</hi> The Engliſh as men indued with new ſtrength from on high, vigorouſly preſt forward, as reſolved to become abſolute van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhers, or to die martyrs. After
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151118:26"/>one hours ſharp diſpute, the <hi>Scots</hi> were wholly routed, their Cavilry fled, and the Infantry were all or moſt of them ſlain and taken to the number of about 15000. There were taken 200 Colours, 10 Collonels, 12 Lievtenant Collonels, 9 Majors, 47 Captains, 72 Lievtenants, 80 En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fignes, befides Cornets and Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters: 22 Pieces of Ordinance, with ſeverall ſmaller Pieces, about 15000 Arms; thoſe of quality taken, were the Lord <hi>Libberten</hi> and his Son, the Lord <hi>Cranſton,</hi> Sr. <hi>James Lumſdale,</hi> Lievtenant Gen. of the Foot, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutant Gen. <hi>Bickerton,</hi> Scoutmaſter Generall <hi>Cambill,</hi> &amp;c. At this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement all the Forces of the Engliſh would not amount to 1200, and the <hi>Scots</hi> were in number more then 20000. And as there was a general Faſt throughout <hi>England,</hi> to implore a bleſſing from Heaven upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of their Army in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo likewiſe there was appointed a ſolemne day of thankſgiving to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for this mighty Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obtained over the <hi>Scots</hi> in the fields of <hi>Dunbar, Sep.</hi> 3. 1650. In the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151118:26"/>whereof many of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy ſhewed themſelves very froward and obſtinate, of whom I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sept.</hi> 7. four Regiments of Foot marched into <hi>Lieth,</hi> where they found 37 Guns mounted on Platforme, ſome Shot and Ammunition with ſtore of wealth.</p>
            <p>The ſame day the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> drew the reſt of his Army both Horſe and Foot into <hi>Edenbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi> without any loſſe ſave the Arm of a Souldier taken off by a Canon bullet from the Caſtle. <hi>Sept.</hi> 6. being Sabbath day, Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent a Trumpeter into the Caſtle, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite the Miniſters to come to their ſeveral Charges, which they reſuſed, ſo that the Engliſh ſupplyed their places.</p>
            <p>For ſome certain time the Army was buſied in compleating the Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications at <hi>Lieth,</hi> the moſt commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Harbour for their accommodation in all <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> (after he had cauſed a Protection for Markets, and Liberty of Trade in <hi>Edenburrough</hi> and <hi>Lieth</hi> to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151118:27"/>be proclaimed by beat of Drum and ſound of Trumpet) marched forward <hi>Sep.</hi> 14. with his Army to <hi>Netheriſh,</hi> ſix miles from <hi>Edenburrough,</hi> leaving Major Generall <hi>Overton</hi> with his Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade behind. <hi>Sep.</hi> 15. the Army marched beyond <hi>Linlithgow,</hi> but (by reaſon of the extremity of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) they were forced to quarter there that night. <hi>Sep.</hi> 16. they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched towards <hi>Falkirk;</hi> and from thence <hi>Sep.</hi> 17. within a mile of <hi>Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Sep.</hi> 18. a Councell of Warre was called, and a Letter drawn up to be ſent into the Town, expreſſing their conſtant affection to, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of the People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which though they had not taken the deſired effect, yet being ſo farre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced into the Countrey with their Army, they now deſired them to take into conſideration their former Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and deliver up that place for the ſervice of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi> A Trumpeter being ſent with the Letter, a Gentleman on foot, with a Pike in his hand met him, and told him they would not let him come in, nor receive his Letter.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:151118:27"/>
            <p>In the afeernoon came a Trumpeter from the <hi>Scots,</hi> deſiring a releaſe of Priſoners upon ranſome: To which Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> anſwered, That they came not thither to make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of Men, or to get gain to themſelves, but for the ſervice and ſecurity of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame day Orders were iſſued forth for the Horſe and Foot to march towards <hi>Sterling,</hi> in order to a ſtorm, Ladders and all other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries being provided for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but the ſtrength of the enemy, and of the place, with other diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages being conſidered, it was reſolved that the Army ſhould draw off; which accordingly they did, <hi>Sep.</hi> 19. and marched to <hi>Linlithgow,</hi> which when the Generall and his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers had viewed, order was given for making ſeverall Works for the ſecurity of the place, conceiving it might make a very conſiderable fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Garriſon, lying in the heart of the Country, between <hi>Edinburrough</hi> and <hi>Sterling:</hi> whence (leaving there five Troops of Horſe, and fix Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151118:28"/>of Foot) Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> with the reſt of the Army marched back to <hi>Edenburrough. Sep.</hi> 23. The Gen. and Officers kept a day of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time the Kirk Party alſo appointed a ſolemne Faſt,
<list>
                  <item>1. To humble themſelves for their too much confidence in the arme of fleſh.</item>
                  <item>2. For the malignity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe of their Army.</item>
                  <item>3. For the Plunderings and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe of their Army when they were in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. For their not ſufficient purging their Army.</item>
                  <item>5. For their Commiſſioners un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and ſurreptitious manner of proſecuting the Treaty with their King, and their crooked wayes in bringing him home.</item>
                  <item>6. For their not ſufficient purging the Kings houſe.</item>
                  <item>7. For the juſt grounds they have, that his Majeſties Repentance was not ſound, nor from the heart.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:151118:28"/>
            <p>From which time to the moneths end, little was done, ſave that Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> took order for the effectuall reducing of the Caſtle of <hi>Edenburrough:</hi> for which purpoſe many miners both Scotch and Engliſh were procured to expedite the buſineſſe. <hi>Sep.</hi> 30. The Engliſh went ſo neer the works of the Caſtle, as they carried away one of the Scots Colours, 300 Muskets with other Arms, without any loſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octob.</hi> 1. The <hi>Scots</hi> Galleries went on in order to ſpringing the Mines, they ſent many great and ſmall ſhot among them, yet nothing retarded the work. <hi>Octob.</hi> 2. The Engliſh made a ſearch in the high Church at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and found there one great Iron Gun, 200 new Muskets, 16 barrels of Pouder, 66 bundles of Bandileers, 200 Swords, 200 new Halberts, 300 new Pikes and two load of Match. That which was done the remaining part of this Moneth, was chiefly to beget a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and compliance with thoſe that diſſented from the King and Kirk, <hi>viz.</hi> Col. <hi>Kerre,</hi> and <hi>Straughan,</hi> and their adherents: for which purpoſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151118:29"/>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent Commiſ. Gen. <hi>Whaley</hi> with his own and another Regiment towards them: in the mean while the Fortifications at <hi>Lieth,</hi> and the mining at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> went on proſperouſly: Then Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> with the reſidue of the Army marched towards <hi>Glaſco,</hi> but finding there lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle encouragement for longer ſtay, they quickly returned, and in their way Garriſoned two ſtrong Houſes, both to enlarge their Quarters, and to prevent the Moſſe-Troopers from ſecuring themſelves there.</p>
            <p>Let the Reader now judge what a dyſaſterous condition this People was in, that when an enemy was in the very heart of the Country, there ſhould be ſo many diſtractions and civill diſcords among themſelves, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the killing and ſlaying one another. One Party in the North was for the King without the Kirk; another Party in the Weſt was for the Kirk without the King; a third was for King and Kirk; and theſe were they then at <hi>Sterling,</hi> that bore the greateſt ſway; <hi>viz.</hi> The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates and Generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151118:29"/>all theſe had their ſwords drawn one againſt the other. When things were at this paſſe, Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent a Letter to the Committee of Eſtates, and another of the ſame to Col. <hi>Kerre</hi> and <hi>Straughan,</hi> much like the former, and produced like effect. Commiſ. Gen. <hi>Whaley</hi> that was ſent with a party towards <hi>Kerre</hi> and <hi>Strau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghan,</hi> accoſted them firſt with a Letter, declaring, <hi>That it was not unknown what Amicable wayes they had uſed, to avoid the effuſion of Chriſtian bloud before and ſince they came into</hi> Scotland, <hi>which though hitherto had been ineffectual, yet they ſhould endeavour the ſame;</hi> Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing further, <hi>that their Arms were ſtill ſtretcht out ready to embrace them, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God ſhould incline them to come in, and that they ſought not domination over them, to enſlave them, nor to depreſſe their Kirk-Government, neither that they ſought their Goods or Eſtates, but to carry on the Lords work: And that if they would ſtill be blinded, and perſiſt in gainſaying and oppoſing, then what further miſery befell their Nation by Famine or Sword, would lie heavy on them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Letter (though ſavouring ſo
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151118:30"/>much of integrity and ingenuity) met with nothing of like nature from their Adverſaries, notwithſtanding their pretended deſire of hearkning to an accommodation.</p>
            <p>For within ſhort a ſpace after Col. <hi>Kerre</hi> ſent a Letter to Commiſſ. Gen. <hi>Whaley</hi> then at <hi>Carliſle,</hi> which being contracted, ſpeaks after this ſort; That though they were not in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity againſt the unjuſt invaſion of the Engliſh, yet were they in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to ſuffer, and ſhould ſubmit to Gods will, either by doing or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, until the time of their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance come; and that if it were their happineſſe to periſh in their duty, it would be a ſufficient mercy to them: and when the perſecution had arrived to its height, their captivity ſhould be returned: adding that he thought it ſtrange the Engliſh ſhould talk of a ceſſation, even while they were captivating their poor people, aſſaulting their Garriſons, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending their godly Miniſters, tearing them from their holy callings, and from their holy ſighing flocks: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, that the departure of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151118:30"/>Engliſh out of that Kingdome, and then deſiring a Chriſtian Treaty or conference with them, would be a favour and mercy equally as great to the one as the other. Theſe were the effects of that (I will not ſay miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided) zeal, by which theſe men were acted.</p>
            <p>About the latter end of this Moneth the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> departed this life,<note place="margin">Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> dies.</note> who ſo lately had put a hook into the Noſtrils, and a Bridle into the mouths of the high and mighty States, and in him the <hi>Scots</hi> King loſt the great intereſt he had in thoſe parts; whom, though the States for his late Actions when he was living hated, yet when dead they lamented:<note place="margin">The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of a Son.</note> About ten dayes after this, the <hi>Princeſſe</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> was delivered of a Son, which did in part mitigate the grief that was conceived for the death of the Prince.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the <hi>Scots</hi> ſtill ſlighted all the wayes and means of a friendly compliance, as appeared by another Letter from Coll. <hi>Kerre</hi> to Commiſſ. Gen. <hi>Whaley,</hi> wherein he adviſes them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſtand upon his Guard, and expect
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151118:31"/>no further Overtures; the Engliſh ſet upon new undertakings, and by a party of Horſe under Major <hi>Brown,</hi> took in a ſtrong place called <hi>Dalhouſe,</hi> and in it filtie Muskets, fiſtie Pikes, four Barrels of Pouder, ſome ſtore of Proviſions and Provender: this was a ſuppoſed Harbour for thoſe villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous people the Moſſe-Troopers who murthered divers Engliſh men ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or going for Proviſions; they likewiſe ſurpriſed a party of Moſſe-Troopers in <hi>Darlington</hi> Caſtle, ſome of which were ſhot preſently upon the place. Then advanced Col. <hi>Monk</hi> with a party of Horſe and Foot to reduce <hi>Roſelane</hi> Caſtle, ſeven miles from <hi>Edinburrough,</hi> which (when he had ſent in ſome Granadoes among them) was yeelded upon mercy. Major Gen. <hi>Lambert</hi> preſently after with a party of 2000 Horſe marched towards <hi>Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freez,</hi> Coll. <hi>Kerre</hi> being then about <hi>Peebles;</hi> Commiſſ. Gen. <hi>Whaley</hi> in his march towards the enemy, took in <hi>Dalkeith</hi> Caſtle with a threatning Summons, where was ſtore of Arms, Ordnance, Pouder, Match and Bullet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the wall of it was thirteen foot broad
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151118:31"/>at the top: Now Coll. <hi>Lambert</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (not without ſome difficultie) got over <hi>Hambleton</hi> River, quartered there that night; Coll. <hi>Kerre</hi> having notice thereof early next morning, reſolved to beat up their Quarters and fall in upon them, and ſo to ſurprize the Major Generall, all which he attempted with courage; but the Engliſh having a timely A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larme,<note place="margin">Col. <hi>Kers</hi> party de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, and himſelf taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</note> on a ſudden encompaſſed moſt of the enemies Horſe of whom they killed 100, and took 100, they took likewiſe 400 Horſe and Furniture, forſook of the Riders, and purſued the reſt as farre as <hi>Ayre;</hi> in which purſuit Collonel <hi>Kerre</hi> himſelfe was wounded and taken, with his Capt. Lievt. Lievtenant Collonell, and <hi>Straughans</hi> Major,<note place="margin">Colonell <hi>Straughan</hi> came in to Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Collonell <hi>Straughan,</hi> Capt. <hi>Giffin,</hi> with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the diſſenters in the Weſt, came then in to the Major General, who brought them all forthwith to the Head-Quarters at <hi>Edenburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>December.</hi> The Engliſh having raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Battery, planted their morter-peece, and great Canon againſt <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> Caſtle, and begun to play; the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151118:32"/>Enemy hung out a Flag of defiance, in contempt thereof: but they had not plaid long ere they took it in, whereby it was conceived ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table execution was done by four or five ſhels that fell among them, and forthwith put out a white Flag on the top of the Caſtle, and ſent forth a Drummer offering to ſurrender, if they might have leave to ſend to the Committee of Eſtates: which being denyed they accepted of a Treaty, and ſent Major <hi>Abernethy</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hinderſon</hi> to treat on their part: Col. <hi>Monk,</hi> and Liev. Col. <hi>White</hi> were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to treat in behalf of the Engliſh, the reſult whereof was to this effect.</p>
            <p>That the Caſtle of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> ſhould be ſurrendred up to his Excellency the Lord General <hi>Cromwell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſtrong and impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Caſtle of <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</note> on the 24. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1650. with all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Arms, Magazine, and Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of Warre thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>That the Governour with all the Officers and Souldiers, ſhould then march forth with their Arms, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours flying, Drums beating; mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151118:32"/>lighted and Bullet in mouth to ſuch place as they ſhall chooſe.</p>
            <p>That ſuch Inhabitants adjacent as have any goods in the Caſtle, ſhall have them reſtored unto them; and to that purpoſe they had liberty from the 19. to the 24. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> to fetch them away. There was taken in this ſtrong hold five French Canon, five Dutch half Canon, two Culverings, two Demi-culverings, two Minion, two Faulcon, 28 Braſſe Drakes, two Petards, about 7000 Arms, 80 Barrels of Pouder, ſtore of Canon Shot, with other proviſions propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable.</p>
            <p>It may ſeem ſtrange and almoſt incredible, that ſuch a ſtrong and impregnable hold, as was that, ſhould be ſo eaſily won, the like whereof is not in that Nation; wherefore it was the common vogue of that time, and by many credibly beleeved, that it was aſſaulted with ſilver engines; But whether it was covetouſneſſe, cowardiſe, Treachery, or want that cauſed this ſudden rendition, I know not: But this I know and am ſure, it made as much for, and was of as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151118:33"/>great importance to the Engliſh, as can be imagined; for while that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe was yet in ſuſpence, the Army was hindred from many attempts of great conſequence.</p>
            <p>Nor was the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> leſſe fortunate in their maritime af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs: for the Engliſh Fleet under the command of Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> lying before <hi>Lizbon,</hi> after they had deſtroyed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall French Pirates, taken many Sugar Prizes belonging to the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> of great value, and ſcowr'd the Seas in ſome ſort of ſuch others as had been ſo extremely prejudicial to the Engliſh Merchants, eſpecially thoſe trading into the Levant Seas; they were conſtrained partly by diſtreſs of weather, and partly to revictuall and water, to make for ſome other port: in which time Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> with his Fleet (making a vertue of neceſſity) hoiſted ſail, and ſteer'd their courſe for <hi>Malaga,</hi> where they burnt and ſpoiled ſeverall Merchants Ships: Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> hereupon reduced his Fleet to ſeven ſtout and nimble Frigots, and ſent the reſt home with the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, and with them he made all the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151118:33"/>Sail he could after the Enemy, and coming to <hi>Malaga,</hi> heard they were gone towards <hi>Alicant,</hi> Generall <hi>Blake</hi> ſailing thence betwixt <hi>Cape degat,</hi> and <hi>Cape de Paulo</hi> took a French Ship of twentie Guns, and preſently after that the Roe-buck one of the revolted Ships fell into their hands, after which they met with the Black Prince another of <hi>Ruperts</hi> Fleet,<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> Fleet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</note> which to avoid being taken, ran aſhoar and blew her ſelf up: next day four more of <hi>Ruperts</hi> Fleet ran aſhoar in the Bay of <hi>Cartagena,</hi> where they were caſt away and bulged: Some few dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Generall <hi>Blake</hi> ſet ſail to ſeek out the reſt of <hi>Ruperts</hi> Fleet, which were two, ſteering his courſe towards <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norca, Majorca, Humattera;</hi> but miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them he gave over the Chaſe, and returned for <hi>England,</hi> having done as much as could be expected from men valiant and faithfull, to the great encouragement of the Merchants, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of the people, and joy of all well-affected people.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, ſeverall deſigns were ſet on foot by unquiet and wayward ſpirits in behalf of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151118:34"/>
               <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> ſome by open inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, others by ſecret combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which the Clergie had no ſmall ſhare, as ſhall be declared here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>There was executed at <hi>Tiburne</hi> one <hi>Benſon</hi> for acting by vertue of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the <hi>Scots</hi> King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Benſon</hi> an Agent from the <hi>Scots</hi> King executed at <hi>Tiburn.</hi>
               </note> being in the ſame conſpiracy with Col. <hi>Andrews</hi> who was beheaded as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſame account roſe a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous rabble in the County of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
               </note> who for a while went roving to and again, pretending the ends of that undertaking, was for the aboliſhing of Popery, reſtoring the young King to his Crowns revenge of his Fathers death, for ſuppreſſion of hereſie and ſchiſm;<note place="margin">Is appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders executed.</note> But as it was begun with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out order, ſo was it managed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſolution: For the Parliament were no time-givers to growing dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, but immediately gave order for the ſuppreſſing them; So that 200 Horſe from <hi>Lyn,</hi> and three Troops of Horſe from the Army, with ſome of the <hi>Militia</hi> Forces of that County, marched towards them, upon which they were preſently diſperſed and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151118:34"/>ſome taken, whereof about twentie were executed, who becauſe they were perſons of no great eminencie, I ſhall forbear troubling the Reader with their Names.</p>
            <p>About this time alſo Sir <hi>Henry Hide</hi> being commiſſionated as Ambaſſador from the <hi>Scots</hi> King to the Grand <hi>Signior</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Henry Hide</hi> exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at the Old Exchange</note> ſtood in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> (then Ambaſſador for the Engliſh) for his place: whereupon they had a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the Vizier <hi>Baſſa,</hi> the reſult whereof was, that Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> ſhould diſpoſe of the ſaid Sir <hi>Henry Hide,</hi> as he thought good, who was ſtraightway ſent to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> and there condemned and executed for a traitor before the Royal Exchange in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The warre in <hi>Scotland</hi> was now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at a ſtand, for the ſharpneſſe of the Winter was ſuch in that Northern Climate, that much could not be expected, yet were all probable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns for the reducing that obſtinate and hardy people put in execution. The <hi>Scots</hi> were chiefly buſied about the Coronation of their King, which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151118:35"/>was performed at <hi>Scone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Scots King crowned at <hi>Scone. Jan.</hi> 30. 1651.</note> 
               <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. 1651. with as much ſolemnity and gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as their neceſſity and poverty would permit; then they proceeded to the excommunication of <hi>Straughan, Swimon,</hi> and others that came in to the Engliſh, made a ſhift to unite the other Diſſenting parties, and then put out an Act for new Levies to be made throughout the Nation.</p>
            <p>Soon after this Lievt. Gen. <hi>David Leſley</hi> with a party of 800. Horſe made an attempt upon <hi>Lithgow</hi> where was a Regiment of Horſe under Col. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> who being preſently in a readineſſe to receive them, the <hi>Scots</hi> retreated without entring the Town.</p>
            <p>Next attempt of the Engliſh was for reducing of <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle with two Regiments of Horſe and Foot,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged.</note> commanded by Col. <hi>Fenwick,</hi> who coming before it ſent in this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which with the anſwer for the unuſual ſtrain thereof I here inſert.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151118:35"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HIS Excellency the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> hath commanded me to reduce this Caſtle you now poſſeſſe, under his obedience, which if you now deliver in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands, for his ſervice, you ſhall have fit terms for your ſelf, and thoſe with you, and eaſe the adjacent parts of a great charge; If you refuſe, I doubt not but in a ſhort time, by the Lords aſſistance to obtain what now I demand. I expect your anſwer by ſeaven of the Clock to morrow morning, and reſt</p>
                  <trailer>To the Governour of <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle.</trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Servant,</hi> George Fenwick.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Have received a Trumpeter of yours, as be tels me, without the Paſſe to render <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle to the Lord Generall <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well:</hi> Pleaſe you I never ſaw your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, nor knew your Generall; as for <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle it stands upon a rock: Given at <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle this day before ſeaven a clock: ſo reſteth without prejudice to my Native Countrey,</p>
                  <trailer>For the Governour of <hi>Barwick.</hi>
                  </trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>Th. Cockburne.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:151118:36"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this reſolute and conceited anſwer,<note place="margin">Aſſaulted and taken.</note> when the Engliſh with their Culverin and Mortar-piece had opened a ſmall breach, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my beat a parley, and becauſe they might not have ſuch conditions as they would, they were forced to take ſuch as they could get, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render upon mercy, which was done accordingly.</p>
            <p>Then Col. <hi>Monk</hi> with about three Regiments of Horſe and Foot, laid Siege to <hi>Tymptallon</hi> Caſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Timptallon</hi> Caſtle ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> againſt which they plaid with their Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-pieces for the ſpace of 48 hours, but did them no hurt; then they plaid at the Caſtle with ſix battering Guns, which did ſuch notable exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, that the enemy beat a parley, and deſired terms to march away, but none would be granted, ſave that they ſhould yeeld themſelves to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which was at laſt accepted, and the Caſtle yeelded, with all the Guns, Arms, Ammunition, and proviſion therein: The taking of this Caſtle was of great concernment to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, who were ever and anon taken and rifled by that Garriſon; So that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151118:36"/>now the paſſage from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> to <hi>Barwick,</hi> was in a manner cleer. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which, and all the care that had been uſed, the Engliſh were daily ſurprized and murdered in ſmall ſtragling parties; inſomuch that General <hi>Cromwell</hi> was forced (for the fafeguard of his men) to publiſh and ſtrictly to put in execution the following Proclamation.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>FInding that divers under my command are not only daily ſpoiled and robbed, but alſo ſometimes barbarouſly and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely ſlain by a ſort of Out-laws and robbers, not under the diſcipline of any Army, and finding that all our tenderneſs to the Country, produceth no better effect, then their compliance with and protection of ſuch perſons, and conſidering that it is in the power of the Countrey to detect and diſcover them, many of them being inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of thoſe places, where commonly the outrage is committed, and perceiving that their motion is ordinarily by the invitation, and according to intelligence given them by Countreymen; I do therefore declare, that whereſoever any under my command, ſhall
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151118:37"/>be hereafter robbed or ſpoiled by ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I will require life for life, and a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſatisfaction for their Goods, of thoſe Pariſhes and places where the fact ſhall be committed, unleſſe they ſhall diſcover and produce the offender; and this I wiſh all perſons to take notice of, that none may plead ignorance.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given under my hand at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> 
                        <date>Novemb. <hi>5. 1650.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>O. Cromwell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Hereupon ſeverall Sums of Mony were levied upon ſuch Pariſhes and places where any Robberies or Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were committed; and likewiſe ſuch perſons as were found to abett, act, or aſſiſt in the perpetrating any murthers, were forthwith condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and executed, according to the tenour of the aforeſaid Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh in the next place de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd the reducing of <hi>Brunt</hi> Iſland, and in order thereto they ſhipped ſome of their Infantry; but either through the Ignorance, miſtake, or neglect of the chiefe Commander,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151118:37"/>the deſign for that time was fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> with his Army mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched from <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and aſſayed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times to paſſe over into <hi>Fife;</hi> but the violent ſeaſon and difficult paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, forced them to betake themſelves to their former Quarters, which were the more comfortable by reaſon of the Fleet of Ships that arrived at <hi>Leith</hi> with plenty of proviſions for Horſe and Man; one whereof bound from <hi>Hamburgh</hi> with Cheeſe, by diſtreſſe of weather, was driven into the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where it was ſeized: but the Maſter pretended he was bound for <hi>Haver de Grace</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing old Cockets, importing as much, he was diſmiſt, and a Scotch-man put himſelf and goods aboard for <hi>France;</hi> whereupon they ſet ſail, and about the <hi>Frith</hi> were boarded by an Iriſh Man of Warre, who would have carryed the Veſſell to <hi>Ireland,</hi> alledging they were bound for <hi>Leith:</hi> the Maſter ſtood to his former relation, and deſired they would take the report of a Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who was aboard; ſo that forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they left her, and ſhe came ſafe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151118:38"/>into <hi>Leith,</hi> whence the Scotchman was ſent home to carry the News. Theſe with many other the ſupplies that were ſent from <hi>England</hi> were a great heartning to the Souldiers in the midſt of thoſe many hardſhips they were expoſed to by diſeaſes, and otherwiſe; of which, the Generall himſelf had as great a ſhare as any, for he had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny violent fits of the contagious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of that Countrey that brought him even to the brink of death; yet the weakneſſe and want of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral did neither abate the Souldiers courage, nor retard the enterprizes they deſigned for compleating their work; although other difficulties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented themſelves, as ſo many moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of oppoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> the number of their enemies diſperſed all along the other ſide of the River to prevent their Landing, the danger of the paſſage it ſelf, and the unſeaſonableneſſe of the weather; theſe Impediments with the weak condition of the Engliſh, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred any further proceedings for ſome ſpace of time.</p>
            <p>During which Intervall there hapned as remarkable an accident in <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:151118:38"/>as any Story can parallel, which for the ſtrangeneſſe and rarity thereof, may well merit my pains to recite, and the Readers patience to peruſe. At <hi>Oxford</hi> (the famous and renowned Nurſery of humane Literature) was tryed, condemned, and executed, <hi>Anne Green,</hi> a Servant to Sir <hi>Thomas Read,</hi> at <hi>Ounſtu</hi> in that ſhire, who being with child by a Gentleman in that Houſe, (as ſhe affirmed to the laſt) about the fourth moneth of her time, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>working herſelf fell in travell, and (not knowing what it might be) went to the Houſe of Office, where with ſome ſtraining, the Child fell from her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aware (as ſhe ſaid) being not above a ſpan long; and ſomething appearing in her Linnen that cauſed ſuſpicion, ſearch was made, and an abortive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant found on the top of the Houſe of Office: ſo that three dayes after, (being in that time before ſome Juſtices of the Peace) ſhe was carried Priſoner to <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anne Green</hi> hanged at <hi>Oxford,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhe revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and in yet alive.</note> where ſhe was condemned, and hanged in the Caſtle-yard: After ſhe had hung about half an hour, (during which time ſhe was pulled by the Legs, and ſtrook on the Breaſt by divers of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151118:39"/>her friends, and others, that ſhe might be out of her pain) ſhe was cut down, put into a Coffin, and brought to a Houſe to be diſſected before ſome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians. When they opened the Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin, they perceived a ratling in her throat, a Fellow ſtanding by, ſtamped upon her breaſt, and belly; yet Doctor <hi>Petty</hi> and two or three more then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, fell ſpeedily to uſe ſome means to bring her to life, and opened a vein, laid her in a warm bed, procured a woman to go into bed to her, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the uſe of divers other remedies, having reſpect to her ſenceleſſneſs, head, throat, and breaſt, ſo that in a few hours ſhe ſpake, the next day talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and coughed very heartily, and in ſhort ſpace perfectly recovered: Upon which firſt her reprieve, and then her pardon was procured: After this, ſhe (as upon the Gallows) ſtill inſiſted upon her innocency and integrity, in relation to the fact for which ſhe was condemned. And indeed this was looked upon as a ſpeciall providence of God, thus to deliver her, who in the judgements of thoſe that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the buſineſſe, was deemed guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151118:39"/>Herein did the hand of God wonderfully appear, in detecting the unadviſed actings of men, and in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us the danger we are in, when we are ſwayed either by paſſion or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt the meaneſt of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>The Parliament weighing how prone the people were to adore the ſhadow of the late King, though the ſubſtance was deſtroyed, cauſed his Statue that was ſet up at the Weſt end of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> to be pulled down, and that alſo in the Royall Exchange, over which they cauſed to be wrote this Motto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exit Tyrannus Regum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimus Anno Libertatis Angliae reſtitutae Primo,</hi> Anno Domini 1648. <hi>January</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>They likewiſe cauſed that badge of Monarchy the Kings Arms, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced and expunged out of all Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Chappels, and places of publick worſhip, and Courts of Judicature, throughout their Dominions: and this indeed was a means to make the gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy people forget the Garlick and Onyons of <hi>Egypt</hi> they much hankered after.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:151118:40"/>
            <p>And to adde a more ſplendid luſtre to their ſtrength and greatneſſe; they were highly courted by Embaſſadors from the Neighbouring Nations, <hi>viz. Holland, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Portugall,</hi> yet the crafty <hi>Hollander</hi> held at a diſtance, as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther willing the proſperity of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all party, then heartily deſiring, or effectually endeavouring a peace with them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniard</hi> as he had better ends, ſo had he better ſucceſſe; though in all his addreſſes he was ſtill reminded of his ſuſpending and delaying the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of juſtice upon the Aſſaſſinates of the Engliſh Reſident at <hi>Madrid,</hi> ſince which time till now the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie between the King and Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that buſineſſe hath been in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Portugall</hi> Embaſſador (after au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience had before a Committee of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,<note place="margin">The Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour diſmiſt home.</note> and ſeveral applications unto them) not being fully impowered, to give a plenary ſatisfaction to the State, for their vaſt expences, and to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants for their great loſſes, all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by them, was at length diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:151118:40"/>
            <p>Embaſſadors extraordinary were ſent from the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to the States of the United Provinces;<note place="margin">Engliſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors are ſent into <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </note> their Names were <hi>Oliver</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Walter Strickland,</hi> men of ſingular parts and of approved integrity, who in gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Equipage, with a magnificent train of followers, ſet ſail from the Downs, <hi>March,</hi> 11. 1651. On the 12. towards Evening, they came to anchor before <hi>Hellevoit ſlugs,</hi> but not without ſome danger: On the 13. they went in Boats to <hi>Roterdam,</hi> being met with Veſſels from the States, then by the Engliſh Merchants were conducted to the Engliſh houſe, and nobly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. During their ſtay there, the Spaniſh Embaſſador ſent a Gentleman to congratulate their ſafe Arrivall, and to deſire there might be a fair corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency and right underſtanding between their Lordſhips and him. About two or three dayes after they ſet forward for the <hi>Hague,</hi> where by the way the Maſter of the Ceremonies, with about thirtie Coaches, met them, and entertained them with ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, and conducted them to a Houſe at the <hi>Hague,</hi> prepared for their
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151118:41"/>reception, where they were feaſted three dayes by the States, and then had audience:<note place="margin">they have audience.</note> where the Lord St. <hi>John</hi> made a Learned and Eloquent Speech in the Engliſh tongue, and then deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a Copy thereof in Dutch and Engliſh, the heads whereof were in effect as follows.</p>
            <p>That they were ſent over to the High and Mighty States of the Netherlands, from the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> to make a firm League and Confederacy between the two Republiques, if they think fit to accept thereof, notwithſtanding the many injuries the Engliſh have ſuſtain'd from the Dutch Nation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To renew and confirm thoſe former Treaties and Agreements of trade and commerce made between the two Nations.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He ſhewed them the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advantages of <hi>England,</hi> in reſpect of the pleaſant and commodious ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation thereof, for the advancement of trade and all other accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, He told them he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Parliament of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151118:41"/>of <hi>England</hi> to let their Lordſhips know how highly they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the Execrable murther of Dr. <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> their Agent, and that he doubted not but that their Lordſhips would uſe their utmoſt care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in cauſing a ſtrict and diligent ſearch to be made after the Authors thereof.</p>
            <p>After which the States (being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the many affronts the Ambaſſadors Gentlemen and others their attendants, had received from Engliſh Cavaliers and other ruffians) drew up a Proclamation and ſent it to the Ambaſſadors by the Lord <hi>Catz,</hi> to know whether they judged it full e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; the contents whereof was, to forbid all manner of perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, from giving any affront, either in word or deed, to any of the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors retinue, upon pain of corporal puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>moneths was now ſpent in this tedious and coſtly Embaſſie, and nothing obtained ſave affronts and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes of all kinds, and the Sword of Juſtice not drawn in their behalfe, againſt any one of that riotous rabble,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151118:42"/>that ſo frequently ſwarmed at the Ambaſſadors gates, aſſaulting their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and reviling their perſons: of which injuries the Parliament being deeply ſenſible, and wearied with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of what fruits this Treaty would produce, reſolved (that ſeeing all their Propoſals and endeavours for a laſting and well grounded Peace, were anſwered with dilatory ſhifts and evaſions, on purpoſe to gain time upon the Engliſh, till they ſaw on which ſide the chance of war in <hi>Scotland</hi> would fall) to call home their Ambaſſadors; which ſudden and unexpected news did ſo ſurprize the Hoghen Mogens, that they courted them with frequent and unuſuall viſits; and with a multitude of feigned expreſſions; laboured to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a good opinion in the Engliſh of the reality of their intentions towards an amicable compliance with this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: notwithſtanding all which the Ambaſſadors ſoon after return into <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>infectapace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which gave further cauſe of jealouſie to the Engliſh, that the Dutch plaid an underhand game with them was, becauſe Admirall <hi>Van-Trump</hi> with a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151118:42"/>Fleet of Ships lay hovering upon the Coaſts of <hi>Scilly,</hi> as though he would make an hoſtile attempt upon that place; but it being demanded of the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> what was the deſign of their Fleet in riding ſo neer that Iſland? It was anſwered that they had no other deſign therein, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand reſtitution of ſuch Ships and Goods, as the Pirates thereof had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from their People: with which anſwer the Parliament were ſomewhat ſatisfied; but not to truſt them too far, ſpeedy order was taken for redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ſame into their own hands.</p>
            <p>Accordingly on the 18.<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>April,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlands of <hi>Scilly</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</note>1651. Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> (with the addition of a ſquadron of Ships commanded by Sr. <hi>George Aiſcue,</hi> that were deſigned for reducing of the <hi>Carybe</hi> Iſlands,) ſet ſail and landed 300 Seamen beſides Landmen upon the Iſle. The Seamen with much reſolution, courage, and gallantry, led the Van, and eaſily made way for the reſt; ſo that they ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came maſters of the Iſlands of <hi>Treſco</hi> and <hi>Briers,</hi> took therein 150 Priſoners, and ſlew about twenty; they took alſo two conſiderable Frigots, the one of 18,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151118:43"/>the other of 32 Guns; they likewiſe became Maſters of the beſt Harbour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to thoſe Iſlands: Hence the enemy fled to St. <hi>Maries,</hi> their chief place of ſtrength, which in ſhort time was ſurrendred. As to the exceeding great ſtrength and commodious ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of theſe Iſlands, I need not ſay much; for who ſo knowes thoſe parts, or hath obſerved the Card, will ſee what a neceſſity there was of reducing the ſame, and what a ſeaſonable mercy God was pleaſed to crown their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours withall, that they ſhould gain ſo conſiderable a place as that, being fortified both by Nature and Art, without the loſſe of ten men, from firſt to laſt.</p>
            <p>Upon miſ-information of the ſtate of <hi>Cornet</hi> Caſtle in the Iſle of <hi>Guernſey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Corner</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Guernſey</hi> aſſaulted, but in vain.</note> that then held out for the Royall party, a conſiderable number of Foot, with Ladders and all things neceſſary, gave an onſet; but whereas it was reported, and beleeved, that there was but fortie men in the Caſtle, and eighteen of them unable for ſervice, it appeared after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that there were ſixtie able men therein, enough to keep it againſt a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151118:43"/>far greater number then was before it, ſo that their Ladders were beaten down and broken with ſtones, timber, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe-ſhot from the flankers, and many of the Souldiers both ſlain and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, inſomuch that it proved a work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo hot for the aſſailants: nor was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here more ſafety in getting off, one or two Boats full of men being ſunk by hot from the Caſtle; but how badly ſoever the buſineſſe ſucceeded, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were not in the leaſt wanting in their duties.</p>
            <p>There was executed at <hi>Towerhill</hi> one that had been a notorious ſtickler for the Royall party by Sea and Land;<note place="margin">Brown Buſhell <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed at</hi> Towerhill.</note> for ſeverall crimes of bloud and treachery acted by him, while he was in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Parliament, and after his revolt known by the Name of <hi>Brown Buſhell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now once more let us advance Northward,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Blackneſſe</hi> taken by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</note> and obſerve the motions of the two Armies: The Engliſh (deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to gain upon their Adverſaries, as much as conſiſted with policy and their own ſafety) with a commanded party under Col. <hi>Monk,</hi> ſet down before <hi>Blackneſſe,</hi> that had much annoyed their
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151118:44"/>Quarters by ſheltring looſe rogues and otherwiſe. After the batteries were made, and ſome ſhot ſpent at it, they deſired Quarter, which (conſidering the ſtrength of the place) was granted and the place ſorthwith yeelded. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the other ſide the <hi>Scots</hi> begun to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both powerfull and numerous to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eye: For notwithſtanding the many parties and Factions, Strifes, Aemula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Contentions, Diviſions, Subdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, Excommunications, &amp;c. they peec't up an agreement (ſuch as it was) to the ſeeming ſatisfaction of all the diſſenters: And now they joyn againſt the common Enemy, having their greateſt hopes wrapt up in a moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deſign and confederacy, hatcht by the Royall Covenanters of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> whereby a generall riſing in the County of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and parts adjacent was contrived; who by joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a conſiderable force from <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſhould have been able to confront the greateſt power the Parliament then had; and this plot had its riſe and progreſſe from the Clergy, thoſe feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datories of Rebellion and Treaſon; but by Gods Providence was ſeaſonably
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151118:44"/>diſcovered; the Grand Agent hereof was <hi>Thomas Cook</hi> of <hi>Grayes Inne</hi> Eſquire, who was apprehended and carryed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Councell of State at White-Hall, whence he made his eſcape, but in few dayes after was retaken at a Houſe in the Strand. Next diſcovery was by means of a Ship bound from the North of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> which by contrary winds was driven into <hi>Ayre,</hi> and there ſecured and ſearcht, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were found many notable Papers, giving further light into the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Not long after this, a Party of Horſe and Dragoons marched to <hi>Grenock,</hi> neer <hi>Dunbarton,</hi> where they ſeized Mr. <hi>Birken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> another Agent for the Royal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, about whom they found ſuch Letters, Commiſſions and Inſtructions, that therein their whole plot was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered: Upon which the Parliament ordered, that a conſiderable body of Horſe and Foot ſhould march North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, under the command of Major Generall <hi>Harriſon,</hi> both to prevent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections and likewiſe to oppoſe the Enemy, if they ſhould make an inrode by the way of <hi>Garliſle.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:151118:45"/>
            <p>At <hi>London</hi> was under queſtion the moſt eminent actors in and contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to the Plot aforeſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> Major <hi>Alford,</hi> Major <hi>Adams,</hi> Col. <hi>Barton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Blackmore,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cauton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Drake,</hi> Capt. <hi>Farr.</hi> Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> Mr. <hi>Haviland,</hi> Major <hi>Huntington,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkings,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jaquel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jackſon,</hi> Lievt. Col. <hi>Jackſon,</hi> Capt. <hi>Muſſey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nalton,</hi> Capt. <hi>Potter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sterks,</hi> Col. <hi>Sowton,</hi> Col. <hi>Vauhan,</hi> and others; of all which there ſuffered only two,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Love</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gibbons</hi> executed.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gibbons:</hi> Now Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by many circumlocutions, ſleights, and evaſions, he ſtrived to clear himſelf, yet beſides the witneſſes of his own party, that teſtified againſt him, he was everted out of his own Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as alſo out of the ſeverall Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions preſented by him to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his own behalf, after he was condemned; which did but procure him a ſhort reſpit from death: for, on the 22. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1651. he with Mr. <hi>Gibbons</hi> aforeſaid, were beheaded on <hi>Tower-hill;</hi> the reſt upon their humble Petitions and acknowledgements of their crimes were releaſt and pardoned.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151118:45"/>And high time it was that ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary piece of juſtice, ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon the proud and obdurate Clergy, who till then thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of the reach of Magiſtratical power, and that their Function might cloak their actions; but let them know that Magiſtracy is an Ordinance of God as well as Miniſtry; for there is no power but of God, and the powers that are, are ordained of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore it would not be amiſſe, if our Governours in ſome particulars would imitate the Republique of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice.</hi> Firſt, By not admitting Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical perſons into ſecular Councels, becauſe they have relation to another Government, <hi>viz.</hi> Pontificiall. 2. By having-a ſpecial care to the Pulpit, and the Preſſe, that no Church-man from the meaneſt Prieſt, to the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, dare tamper with the Affairs, deſigns, or tranſactions of the State:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Howels</hi> Survey of the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory of <hi>Venies.</hi>
               </note> It being too well known (ſaith my Author) that Church-men are the moſt perilous and pernicious inſtruments in a State, if they miſapply their Talents, to poyſon the hearts of the people, to intoxicate their brains, ſuſcitate them
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151118:46"/>to ſedition and a miſlike of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and they have more power to do this, in regard they have the ſway over the nobleſt part of the creature, the ſoul and intellectuals: therefore if any meddle with State-matters in the Pulpit, they are puniſht in an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſevere manner, and this (ſaith he) is alledged for one main reaſon why the <hi>Venetian</hi> Republique hath kept their Liberties inviolable; and if it ſhall pleaſe God to put it into the hearts of our Governours, to take the like courſe, no doubt but we ſhall have the like bleſſing.</p>
            <p>There hapned much about this time a petty inſurrection in <hi>Wales,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A riſing in <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </note> two or three hundred being got together in behalf of the <hi>Scots</hi> King, whom tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale Fame (that hath continuall cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the fickle multitude) had poſſeſt with pleaſing (and yet untrue) news of the defeating Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Army, and the advance of the <hi>Scots</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> which proſperous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt had an event ſuitable to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, <hi>viz.</hi> confuſion and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh being now deſirous to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151118:46"/>put a period to the warre in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by gaining a paſſage over the River in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Fife,</hi> for the facilitating their work, and more eaſie tranſportation, cauſed ſeverall boats to be made, with which they gave many great Alarms to the Enemy on the other ſide, as alſo to thoſe in <hi>Brunt</hi> Iſland, in order to what they further intended.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> alſo made many infalls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the out-quarters and Garriſons of the Engliſh, wherein they had fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently good ſucceſſe, killing ſome, and ſlaying others, having the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Engliſh by their knowledge of the Countrey: for prevention where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, orders were given out for drawing off their remoteſt Garriſons, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting their Quarters, which was done accordingly, and the Army put into a marching poſture for <hi>Fife,</hi> for which purpoſe <hi>Blackneſſe</hi> was made their Magazine; but the Ground not yet affording either Graſſe, or Oats, the enterprize was further ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> having compleated their Levies to the Number of 15000 Foot, and 6000 Horſe, marched on this ſide
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151118:47"/>
               <hi>Sterling,</hi> to a place called <hi>Torwood,</hi> where they were faced by the Engliſh, but would not be drawn to an Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet ſtill lay encamped behind bogs, and inacceſſible faſtneſſes, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to delay the Warre: Upon which the Engliſh reſolved to land ſome For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on <hi>Fife</hi> ſide,<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh gain a paſſage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver into <hi>Fife.</hi>
               </note> and for that end there was drawn out 1600 Foot, and four Troops of Horſe commanded by Col. <hi>Overton,</hi> who attempted to land at Queens Ferry, which on the 17 of <hi>July,</hi> 1651. with the loſſe of about ſix men was effected, and preſently they fell to intrench themſelves: while this was doing, the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> with his Army marcht cloſe up to the Enemy, that in caſe they had marcht towards <hi>Fife,</hi> he might have engaged their rear before they could have reacht <hi>Sterling:</hi> The <hi>Scots</hi> receiving the Alarm the ſame day, forthwith ſent a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable party of Horſe and Foot to the number of 4000 under Sir <hi>John Brown</hi> to drive the Engliſh out of <hi>Fife:</hi> upon which Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent Major Gen. <hi>Lambert</hi> with two Regiments of Horſe and two of Foot to re-enforce the other party, who in 24 hours were
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151118:47"/>ferryed over, and joyned, upon which Col. <hi>Okey</hi> with his Regiment fell in among the Enemy, whereby they were forced to draw into a Battalia, as did the Engliſh alſo, who were more in number then the Enemy, though to equalize that they had greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of ground. In this poſture they continued, facing each other about an hour and half; whereupon the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh reſolved to attempt the Enemy by aſcending the Hill, which being done (after a ſhort diſpute) the <hi>Scots</hi> were utterly routed, 2000 or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts were ſlain,<note place="margin">4000 of the <hi>Scots</hi> routed, ſlain and taken.</note> and 1400 taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, whereof Sir <hi>John Brown</hi> the Commander in chief was one, with Col. <hi>Buchanan,</hi> and many others of quality. Of the Engliſh there was few ſlain, but many wounded: A fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther additional ſtrength of Horſe and foot were ſent into <hi>Fife,</hi> ſo to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Engliſh that they might be able to encounter the whole body of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, if occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Immediately upon this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inchigar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey</hi> Caſtle ſurrendred to the Engliſh.</note> was ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the Engliſh the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Inchigarvey,</hi> ſituate on a rock in the midſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151118:48"/>of the <hi>Fryth,</hi> between <hi>Queens-Ferry</hi> and <hi>North-Ferry,</hi> wherein were 16 pieces of Ordnance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 27. The whole Engliſh Army appeared before <hi>Brunt</hi> Iſland, and ſent in a Summons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brunt</hi> Iſland ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</note> for rendition thereof, unto which the Governour returned a modeſt anſwer, and the next day ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted a Parley: Commiſſioners on both ſides were choſen, and after ſome debate it was agreed that the ſaid Iſland, with all the Proviſions, Guns, and Shipping of Warre, ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into the hands of the Engliſh <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that all the Officers and Souldiers in the ſaid Iſland, ſhould march away with Colours flying, Matches lighted, and Bullet in mouth. This place was of much concernment to the Engliſh, and ſerved for a ſtorehouſe of all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſupplies for the ſupport of their Army.</p>
            <p>Thence the Army marched without ſtay to St. <hi>Johns</hi> Town,<note place="margin">St. <hi>Johns</hi> Town yeelded to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</note> a place of great ſtrength and importance, into which the enemy had newly boated a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Foot: yet when the Engliſh broke down their ſluces, and let the water out of the Graff, the enemies cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151118:48"/>failed them, ſo that it was in ſhort ſpace delivered.</p>
            <p>This was no ſooner done, but the main body of the Engliſh Army, were conſtrained to attend more eminent ſervice, <hi>viz.</hi> the purſuit of the <hi>Scots</hi> King, who with an Army of about 16000 Horſe and Foot,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> enter <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by the way of <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
               </note> had ſlipt into <hi>England</hi> by the way of <hi>Carliſle:</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly moſt of the Infantry were boat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over to <hi>Leith,</hi> with as much expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as could be, and preſently after the Horſe: Orders were immediately given to Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> to march with 3000 Horſe and Dragoons, and (if he could) to get into the rear of the enemy. Major Gen. <hi>Harriſon</hi> was ordered likewiſe to to get into their van, to ſtop them, and do what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he thought fit: beſides theſe there was about ſixteen Regiments of Horſe and Foot, with Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> upon their march after the Enemy: And to proſecute the affairs of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Liev. Gen. <hi>Monk</hi> was left with a party of 7000 Horſe and Foot, who ſtraightway took in the ſtrong Town and Caſtle of <hi>Sterling, Aberdeen, Abernethy, Dundee, Dunotter</hi> Caſtle, <hi>Dunbarton</hi> Caſtle, with
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151118:49"/>ſeverall others, ſo that the whole Realme of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was (after a paſſage gained into <hi>Fife</hi>) with little or no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty ſubdued and made tributary to the Republick of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> Army,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> enter the City of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
               </note> after many halts and skirmiſhes, long and tedious mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, weakned in their bodies, and diſtracted in their minds, decreaſing rather then increaſing, at length put into <hi>Worceſter;</hi> whence the King ſent out his Letters mandatory to Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Middleton</hi> to raiſe forces for him, and to Col. <hi>Mackworth,</hi> Governour of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> to the like purpoſe, as he did to others alſo, but without ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. He was likewiſe proclaimed King of <hi>Great Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in moſt places where he came: which blaſt of Honour (like <hi>Jonah</hi>'s Gourd) quickly vaniſht: for alas by this project of theirs, of coming into <hi>England,</hi> they run themſelves into in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable danger, as the Poet ſayes,
<q>Decidit in Scyllam, qui vult vitare Charyb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dim;</q> being invironed on all ſides with the Militia Forces of the ſeverall Counties
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151118:49"/>of the Nation, beſides Gen. <hi>Cromwels</hi> Army they ſo much dreaded; there was likewiſe a conſiderable body of Horſe and Foot under Major Gen. <hi>Lambert</hi> and <hi>Harriſon</hi> that attended their motions. Col. <hi>Robert Lilburne</hi> was left in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> to hinder the Earl of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> from raiſing Forces in thoſe parts; other parties were diſpoſed into ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall other places, to hinder the enemy of Proviſion, or ſtop their flight as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhould be.M</p>
            <p>The Earle of <hi>Derby</hi> being landed (as was expected) at <hi>Wyewater</hi> in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire,</hi> with about 300 Gentlemen and others, endeavoured to raiſe the Country, while the Engliſh were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and in ſhort ſpace by the acceſſion of Papiſts, Royaliſts, and diſcontented Presbyterians, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed to the number of 1500: Gen. <hi>Cromwells</hi> Regiment of Foot being then at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> was appointed to meet Col. <hi>Lilburne</hi> at <hi>Preſton:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> routed in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi>
               </note> To prevent this conjunction, the enemy bent their courſe towards <hi>Marcheſter</hi> to ſurprize the ſaid Regiment; whereupon Col. <hi>Lilburne</hi> aſſay'd to flank the enemy in their march, and by that means to joyn
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151118:50"/>with thoſe Foot; which the enemy perceived, and preſt to engage. Now though Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> was overmatcht with Foot in point of number, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the diſpute proved tedious and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, yet in the ſpace of an hour, the enemy was totally routed, many perſons of quality were taken, as Col. <hi>Leg,</hi> Col. <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> Col. <hi>Bayns,</hi> Col. <hi>Gerard,</hi> 4 Lievt. Col. 1 Major, 4 Captains, 2 Lievtenants, 20 Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Reformadoes, 500 Common Souldiers, with all their baggage, Sumpters, Arms and Ammunition, the Earl of <hi>Derby</hi>'s George, Garter, and other Robes with badges of the Order, but he himſelf eſcaped and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered <hi>Worceſter:</hi> There were ſlain the Lord <hi>Widrington,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſly,</hi> Col. <hi>Matth. Boynton,</hi> Sir <hi>William Throgmorton,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Gamuel,</hi> with ſome other inferior Officers, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 60 private Souldiers. Of the Parliaments party but ten were ſlain, but many wounded: For this piece of ſervice Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> was bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rewarded, as he indeed deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> (who by delayes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151118:50"/>contributed to approaching dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) with his Army came to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> before he was either deſired or expected by his Adverſaries; when as the whole Army was preſently diſpoſed about the City, in order to a cloſe begirting thereof.</p>
            <p>The firſt remarkable attempt, was the poſſeſſing a Paſſe upon the <hi>Severne,</hi> at a place called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pton,</hi> which was done by a party led on by Major Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> and was preſently made good by Lievt. Gen. <hi>Fleetwoods</hi> Brigade, who marched towards the River <hi>Teame,</hi> over which was made a Bridge of Boats, and another over <hi>Severn</hi> on the Generals ſide; upon which the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my took the Alarme, and drew out Horſe and Foot, to oppoſe the Lievt. Generals paſſage; to whoſe relief there was commanded over Collonel <hi>Ingles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes,</hi> and Col. <hi>Fairfax</hi> Regiments of Foot, the Generals Lifeguard, and Col. <hi>Hackers</hi> Regiment of Horſe; all which were led on by Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> in perſon: then was commanded over likewiſe Col. <hi>Goffs,</hi> and Major Gen. <hi>Deans</hi> Regiments, who fell to ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hedges, which the enemy had
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151118:51"/>lined, and beat them from hedge to hedge, and being ſeconded by a freſh ſupply (after about an hours ſharp diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute) the enemy was forced to give ground and fly to <hi>Powick</hi> Bridge, where with about three Regiments more they maintained another hot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, but at length quitted their ground alſo, and ran into <hi>Worceſter,</hi> except ſome that were taken.</p>
            <p>After which (renewing their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage) they drew out what Horſe and Foot they could on the Generals ſide, thinking moſt of his Army had been on the other ſide, making a bold and reſolute ſally, whereby the Generalls men were forced a little to retire; but the ſcales preſently turned, and in ſuch ſort that the enemy was totally routed,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> routed at <hi>Worceſter, Sept.</hi> 3. 1651.</note> both Horſe and Foot, their Works, and Fort-Royall were taken, and their Canon turned upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Town alſo was ſtraightway entred and ſacked; moſt of the <hi>Scots</hi> Infantry were ſlain and taken, but of their Horſe above 3000 eſcaped, of which Col. <hi>Barton</hi> lying about <hi>Bewdly</hi> with ſome Horſe and Dragoons, took neer upon a thouſand; Col. <hi>Lilburne</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151118:51"/>with the Generalls Regiment of Foot, met with the Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> that late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo narrowly miſt his hands, with the Earl of <hi>Lauderdaile</hi> and above an hundred perſons of quality more. In this engagement and the gleanings thereof, there were taken priſoners neer 10000, and about 3000 ſlain: Thoſe of Quality taken, were Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Earl <hi>Lauderdaile,</hi> Earl of <hi>Rothes</hi> Earl of <hi>Carnwath,</hi> Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> Sir <hi>John Packington,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningham,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Clare,</hi> Lord <hi>Spine,</hi> Lord <hi>Sinclare,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cleveland,</hi> Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> Earl of <hi>Kelly,</hi> Col. <hi>Graves,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Fanſhaw,</hi> Secretary to the <hi>Scots</hi> King: 6 Col. of Horſe, 13 of Foot, 9 Lievt. Col. of Horſe, 8 of Foot, 6 Majors of Horſe, 13 Majors of Foot, 37 Capt. of Horſe, 72 Capt. of Foot, 55 Quartermaſters of Horſe, 89 Lievtenants of Foot; Major Gen. <hi>Pitſcotty,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Montgomery,</hi> the Lievt. Gen. of the Ordnance, Adjut. Generall of the Foot, the Marſhall, Quartermaſter Generall, and Waggon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter Generall: 76 Cornets of Horſe, 99 Enſigns of Foot, 30 of the Kings Servants, 9 Miniſters, 9 Chirurgions,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151118:52"/>158 Colours, the Kings Standard, Coach and Horſes, with other rich goods, and his Collar of SS. Many Parties were taken beſides in ſeverall other places, as <hi>Warwickſhire, Shropſhire, Lancaſhire, Cheſhire, Yorkſhire,</hi> &amp;c. inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that few of that great Body eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, but were either killed or taken. Major Generall <hi>Maſſey</hi> being ſorely wounded, ſurrendred himſelf to the Counteſſe of <hi>Stamford,</hi> and by the Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Groby</hi> her Sonne, was ſecured and ſent to <hi>London,</hi> whence in ſhort ſpace he made an eſcape: In another place was taken Major Gen. <hi>Middleton,</hi> and Lievt. Gen. <hi>David Leſley;</hi> ſo that I may ſay, the gleanings of this Victory were not much inferior to the harveſt thereof.</p>
            <p>Neer this time, moſt of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Gentry of <hi>Scotland,</hi> were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at a place called <hi>Ellet</hi> in that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where they were aſſembled to propagate the Royall deſigns: <hi>viz.</hi> Old Gen. <hi>Leſley,</hi> Earl Marſhall, Lord of <hi>Keith,</hi> Earl of <hi>Craford,</hi> Lord <hi>Ogilby,</hi> Lord <hi>Burgoiny,</hi> Lord <hi>Huntly,</hi> Lord <hi>Lee,</hi> with many Knights, Gentlemen and Miniſters: all which were ſoon after
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151118:52"/>ſhipped and ſent for <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such was the fate that attended the <hi>Scots</hi> and their King, that he who a few dayes before was proclaimed King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> had now neither Camp nor Garriſon, nor lodging to flie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or ſafely to repoſe himſelf in for ſhelter, 500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> ſterling being offered to any that ſhould detect him; which notwithſtanding he eſcaped, making a diſguiſed peregrination through City and Country, till he met with a fit opportunity for his tranſportation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France,</hi> where he now is. Yet of the great number of his friends, adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and followers that were taken, none of quality ſuffered but the Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note> who was beheaded at <hi>Bolton</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and Sir <hi>Tim. Fetherſton,</hi> others of leſſe note were executed at <hi>Chester, Shrewsbury</hi> and other places.</p>
            <p>Nor did the Royalliſts themſelves expect any other or better fortune would attend them in this invaſion, then that you have heard; as appears by Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Letter to Mr. <hi>Will-Crofts,</hi> taken among other Papers, a few dayes before the fight, the ſumme whereof follows.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:151118:53"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>WE are all laughing at the ridiculouſneſse of our condition,<note place="margin">Duke <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miltons</hi> Letter.</note> who having quit <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> being ſcarce able to maintain it; yet we graſp at all, and nothing but all will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie us, or to loſe all: I confeſſe I cannot tell whether our hopes or fears are greateſt; but we have one ſtout Argument, and that is deſpair, for we muſt now either ſhortly fight or die. All the Rogues have left us, I will not ſay whether for fear or diſloyalty; but all now with his Majeſty are ſuch as will not diſpute his Commands.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>So that you ſee, this undertaking was not the product of a mature and deliberate counſell, but of neceſſity and deſperation.</p>
            <p>Soon after this the Parliament took order for reducing the two Iſlands of <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> that had been and would ſtill be notable receptacles, for the entertaining all manner of Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and diſaffected perſons.</p>
            <p>In order to which buſineſſe, Col. <hi>Hayne</hi> with about two Regiments of Foot and two Troops of Horſe, on
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151118:53"/>the 14. of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1651. were ſhipt at <hi>Weymouth</hi> for <hi>Jerſey;</hi> they were in all eighty Veſſels, and ſet ſayl <hi>Octob.</hi> 17. but a ſtorm forced them in again. On the 19 they ſet ſail again, and about 12 that night came to an Anchor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Sark</hi> Iſland, next morning they bent their courſe towards <hi>Jerſey,</hi> and came to an Anchor in St. <hi>Owens</hi> Bay; next day they ſailed and Anchored before St. <hi>Brelades</hi> Bay, when the ſeas proved ſo rough that the Fleet was ſcattered; notwithſtanding on the 21 it was reſolved that an attempt ſhould be made upon the Iſland that night at St. <hi>Owens</hi> Bay, being neceſſitated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto for want of Horſemeat; in few hours after they embarked their men aboard the ſmall Boats, Gen <hi>Blake</hi> and all his Officers were very active in this buſineſſe, who about two hours after the floud, weighed Anchor, cut ſome of their Cables, hoiſted ſails and ſtood in for the ſhoare, and were ſoon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground on the ſhoare ſide, ſome at three foot, ſome at four, five, ſix, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſoot water; their men preſently leapt out, ſome up to the middle, ſome to the neek, and ran aſhoare;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151118:54"/>the enemy playing hard upon them with great and ſmall ſhot, and with their Horſe gave a hot charge; yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter half an hours diſpute, they fled and left behind them 12 Guns, and ſome Colours at that place; after which and that their Horſe were lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they marched further into the Iſland, and on the 23. of <hi>Octob.</hi> poſſeſt themſelves of three Forts more with two Guns in each; they marched on further till they came within ſight of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Caſtle, under which was a Fort called St. <hi>Albans</hi> Tower, where was 14 Guns, the ſpeedy reducement whereof was reſolved upon,<note place="margin">The Iſland of <hi>Jerſey</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</note> and a Summons ſent in, and in two hours time it was delivered up. The next buſineſſe they had to do, was to take in Mount <hi>Orgueil</hi> Caſtle, which upon eaſie tearms was alſo ſurrendred. But <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Caſtle being a place of farre greater ſtrength, was not reduced till the middle of <hi>Decemb.</hi> following; the Governour thereof Sir <hi>George Carteret,</hi> had large tearms granted both to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and all with him, by reaſon of the marvellous ſtrength and ſituation thereof, which was ſuch as might have
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151118:54"/>coſt much blood, treaſure and time in the gaining of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octob.</hi> 16. 1651. Under Collonell <hi>Duckenfield</hi> were ſhipt three Regiments of Foot, <hi>viz.</hi> Gen. <hi>Cromwells</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment commanded by Lievtenant Col. <hi>Worſly,</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Dean</hi>'s Regiment, commanded by Lievt. Col. <hi>Mitchell,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Duckenfields</hi> Regiment, with two Troops of Horſe, theſe were all ſhipt at <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Liverpool</hi> for the reducing the Iſle of <hi>Man:</hi> and on <hi>Octob.</hi> 18. they hoiſted ſail, but by contrary winds, were driven into the Harbour of <hi>Beumorris,</hi> on the 25. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two in the morning, the wind coming about ſomewhat Southerly, with a pretty freſh gale, they ſet ſail again, and about two or three a clock in the afternoon, they had a cleer view of the <hi>Calf</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> Caſtle <hi>Ruſhen, Derby</hi> Fort, <hi>Douglas</hi> Fort, and moſt part of the Iſland, as alſo of the Iſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, both Horſe and Foot in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall motions, muſtering up what ſtrength they could: when by a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſtorm the Fleet was hindred from coming up any thing neer the ſhoar; upon which they ſteered their courſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151118:55"/>towards the North end of the Iſland, and with no ſmall difficultie fetcht <hi>Ramſey</hi>-Bay that night, where they caſt Anchor, and with a ſmall Party ſaced the Iſlanders, yet was there no ſhot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed. <hi>Octob</hi> 16. came on board an Iſlander, imployed by the chief of that Iſland, to aſſure the Engliſh they ſhould have no oppoſition in landing, but might ſecurely come under their Forts, which they had taken poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of, for them, and that only two Caſtles held out, <hi>viz.</hi> Caſtle <hi>Ruſhen,</hi> and Caſtle <hi>Peele,</hi> which were kept by the Forces of the Count of <hi>Derby:</hi> now becauſe he had nothing in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to confirm what he had ſaid, he was diſtruſted; wherefore Major <hi>Fox</hi> was boated into the Iſland, to enquire the truth of what the Iſlander had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and forthwith returned with the full confirmation thereof; and preſently after ſome came from the Iſland as Commiſſioners, entreating that their poor Iſland might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from ſpoyl, and the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants from undoing; by landing only ſome part of a Regiment, or at the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, but a Regiment; upon which,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151118:55"/>they would bring Proviſions at a marketable rate, to the ſhoar,<note place="margin">The Iſle of <hi>Man</hi> reduced.</note> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the wants of ſuch as ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue on ſhipboard, and would aſſiſt thoſe that were to land; in reducing the Caſtles: which Propoſals were in part aſſented unto by the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chief Col. <hi>Duckenfield,</hi> being ſomewhat obliged thereto by the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities of the people. But on the 27. moſt of the men on ſhipboard were endangered by a long and continued ſtorm, many of the Veſſels not being able to ride in the Bay: one ran aſhore and was bulged, but the men ſaved, many others were driven ſeverally up and down; which dangers by ſea, and delayes by land, the Caſtles ſtill hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out; on the 28. Horſe and Foot were ordered to come on ſhoar, and being poſſeſt of all the Forts in the Iſland,<note place="margin">Caſtle <hi>Peele</hi> and <hi>Ruſhen</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> they beſieged both the Caſtles of <hi>Peele</hi> and <hi>Ruſhen,</hi> in which the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Derby</hi> then was, both which were preſently ſummoned and brought to very low terms, without any bloud ſhed; and delivered up to Col. <hi>Due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenfield</hi> for the uſe of the Parliament of <hi>England, Octob.</hi> 26. 1651. Where
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151118:56"/>was found ſtore of Ammunition and Proviſion of all ſorts, and in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſome Veſſels alſo were taken: Theſe Caſtles were of ſuch ſtrength, that if it had pleaſed God the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants had not been poſſeſt with a ſpirit of fear, much bloud might have been ſpent in the reducing of them.</p>
            <p>In ſhort ſpace after there was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to the Parliaments Forces,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cornet</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Guernſey</hi> ſurrender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> that ſtrong and impregnable hold of <hi>Cornet</hi> Caſtle in the Iſle of <hi>Guernſey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next remarkable paſſage of the Affairs of this Nation, was the deceaſe of two of the Parliaments Chieftains, one was Generall <hi>Popham,</hi> one of the Admirals of the Engliſh Fleet, a man of ſingular worth and gallantry; yet his ſhort continuance in that employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did not ſo much ſhew us what he was, as what he would have been, had it pleaſed the great Diſpoſer of all things to have prolonged his dayes.</p>
            <p>The other was the never to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Henry Ireton</hi> Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> under his Father in Law his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> who ended his dayes ſhortly after the ſiege
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151118:56"/>and taking of <hi>Limrick</hi> in <hi>Ireland:</hi> a man who for piety, prudence and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy in Civill and Martiall affairs, equaled if not excelled the moſt of men: yet was there left behind ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Patriots, and Champions of their Country, as upon all occaſions have ſtood in the gap of the greateſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties.</p>
            <p>The Parliament (being now through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of the many delayes, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and wrongs, for a long time, and even now practiſed by the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> both in their Treaties and traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique) ſet forth an Act for encreaſe of Shipping, and encouragement of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, which was the moſt pleaſing and advantageous Act to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Seamen that could be, and by which the hearts of thoſe rough ſpirited men were more endeared to the Parliaments Intereſt, then by any thing they ever did, or could do: the heads whereof were theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That no Commodity whatſoever of the growth or Manufacture of</hi> Aſia, Africa,<note place="margin">The Act for Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</note> 
               <hi>or</hi> America, <hi>or any part thereof, as well of the Engliſh Plantations as others, ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported into</hi> England, Ireland, <hi>or any the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151118:57"/>territories thereof, in any ſhips or Veſſels, but in ſuch only as do truly belong to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth or the Plantations thereof, under penalty of the forfeiture of Goods and Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels: and of</hi> Europe <hi>the like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That no Commodities whatſoever of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign growth or manufacture, which are to be brought into this Commonwealth in Ships belonging to the People thereof, ſhall be by them ſhipped from any places, but only from thoſe of the ſaid growth, production or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture; or from thoſe Ports where the ſaid Commodities can only be, or uſually have been ſhipt for tranſportation, and from none other places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That no ſorts of Fiſh uſually caught by the people of this Nation, nor any Oyl made of Fiſh, nor any Whale, Finne or Whalebones, ſhall be imported, as aboveſaid, but only ſuch as ſhall be caught in Veſſels belonging to the people of this Nation, under the former pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That no kinds of ſalted Fiſh, from the firſt of</hi> February, 1653. <hi>ſhall be exported out of this Land, in any other ſave Engliſh Veſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Severall other Exceptions and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſoes there was in reſerence to the Commodities of <hi>Eaſt-India,</hi> from the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151118:57"/>Levant Seas, from the Ports of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugall:</hi> This is the ſubſtance of that Act which did ſo exceedingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex the avaritious, greedy and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching <hi>Hollander.</hi> Who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſet on foot another Treaty with the Engliſh, by ſending Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors extraordinary, and ſeeing they could not obtain their deſires thereby, they aſſayed to do it by force and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery: which machinations, God (in mercy to this poor Nation) by weak inſtruments, detected and turned upon their own heads: yet could they have procured the calling in of that Act, they would hardly have ſtuck at any other the demands of the Engliſh; but failing therein, they began to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute that antient and unqueſtionable Right of the Engliſh Soveraignty in the narrow Seas, by refuſing to ſtrike therein, for which they had the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to be always beaten, not thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in any ſuch contempt or brava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do; upon which occaſion began that ſad breach between the two Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, the effects whereof we yet feele and groan under; from which God in his good time will deliver us.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:151118:58"/>
            <p>For in <hi>May,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The firſt Sea-fight between the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </note> 1652. <hi>Van-Trump</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of the Dutch Fleet, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 42 ſail of Ships, was diſcovered on the backſide of the <hi>Goodwin-ſands</hi> by Major <hi>Bourn,</hi> who commanded a ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of the Engliſh Ships, the Dutch bearing towards <hi>Dover-Road:</hi> upon which the Grey-hound Frigot was commanded to make ſail and ſpeak with them, which ſhe did, and then they ſtrook their top-ſayl, demeaned themſelves civilly and ſaid, they came from Admirall <hi>Trump,</hi> with a Meſſage to the Commander in chief of the Engliſh Fleet: And coming aboard they ſaluted our Ships, and in order to the ſatisfaction of our Nation, brought this accompt: That the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly winds having blown hard ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dayes, they were forced further Southward then they intended, and having rode for ſome dayes off <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> where they had loſt divers An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors and Cables, profeſſing they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no injury to the Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> with the reſt of the Engliſh Fleet, was at that time to the Weſtward; but receiving ſpeedy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of all theſe paſſages from Major
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151118:58"/>
               <hi>Bourne</hi> made what haſte poſſibly he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ply towards them; and on the 19 of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lay</hi> in the morning, he ſaw them at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nchor about <hi>Dover-Road,</hi> and being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ithin three Leagues of them, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eighed and ſtood to the Eaſtward, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>here they met with an Expreſſe from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e States: whereupon he baſtned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith all the ſayl he could make to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ours, and bore directly up with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Fleet, <hi>Van-Trump</hi> being the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt.</p>
            <p>Upon which Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> ſhot three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uns at <hi>Van-Trumps</hi> Flag, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut Balls, and <hi>Van-Trump</hi> anſwered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith a Gun on the averſe ſide of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip, ſignifying a diſdain, and in ſtead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f ſtriking his top-ſayl, hung out a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Flag, which was the ſignall for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is whole Fleet, and gave Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> broad-ſide; this was the manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he beginning of that Fight which hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſed ſo much trouble to the two Commonwealths; the continuance was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or about four hours, untill night par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed them, in which fight one of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utch Ships was ſunk, and another of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Guns taken, with the Captains of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth, and about 150 Priſoners; of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151118:59"/>the Engliſh there were about ten ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and fortie wounded: the Engliſh A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall received much hurt in her Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Sails, and Rigging, many ſhot w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> likewiſe placed in her Hull, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hurt that was done to the reſt of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Fleet was not conſiderable.</p>
            <p>This attempt of the Dutch wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they were upon a Treaty, did ſo i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the Parliament, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the addreſſes and overtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of their Ambaſſadours, and the comi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> over of two more, they could not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> peaſe them without ſatisfaction for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> injury.</p>
            <p>Although in ſeverall Papers put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Councell of State they labour to excuſe the ſame, alledging,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the unhappy Fight between the Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of both Commonwealths,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the Dutch Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours for the late affront of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh in the <hi>Downs.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>did happen with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the knowledge and againſt the wills of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lords States Generall of the Netherland taking God the ſearcher of mens hearts witneſſe the ſame: and that by Letters a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Meſſages, they were dayly aſſured of the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of their ſaid Lords, and that with gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and aſtoniſhment they received the ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> News of that unhappy raſh action; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereupon fell into conſultatation about a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151118:59"/>to mitigate that raw and bloudy wound: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d to that end had appointed a ſolemn meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g of all the Provinces, whereby they doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not (but by Gods favour) ſuch preſent cure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theſe troubles may be wrought, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t only the outward cauſe of all further e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls may be taken away, but alſo by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne comfort, the minds may be redreſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd reduced again, to a better hope of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reaty in hand; and that this thing was moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rneſtly agitated by their Lords for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on good of both Nations, to ſhun the detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le ſhedding of Chriſtian bloud, ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſired by the enemies of both Nations: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey therefore erave and beſeech this Honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble Councell, by the pledges of common Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gion and Liberty, to ſuffer nothing to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one out of too much heat, that afterwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ay prove neither revocable nor repairable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y too late idle vows and wiſhes; but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey might without delay receive a kind An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; which they deſire ſo much the more, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecauſe the Ships of their Lords and Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, as well in the broad Sea, as in the Ports <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>f this Commonwealth, ſome by force and ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y fighting are kept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which the Parliament reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d,</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:151118:60"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That calling to mind with what cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued demonſtrations of friendſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Anſwer to and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution thereupon.</note> 
               <hi>they hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> demeaned themſelves towards their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the united Provinces, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of their inteſtine troubles, omitting nothing that might tend to a good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with them, do find themſelves muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſurprized with the uNſuitable returns tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have been made thereunto, and eſpecially a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Acts of Hoſtility lately committed in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very roads of</hi> England, <hi>upon the Ships o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Commonwealth: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon conſideration o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all which, and of the ſeverall Papers deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the Ambaſſadors into the Councel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of State, they further anſwered: That as they would be willing to make a charitable conſtruction of the expreſſions in the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, endeavouring to repreſent the late En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of the Fleets to have hapned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Knowledge, and against the Mind of their Superiors; So when they conſider how diſagreeable to that Profeſſion, the Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Actions of your State, and their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters at Sea, have been in the midſt of a Treaty offered by themſelves, and managed here by their Ambaſſadours; the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary preparations of an hundred and fiftie ſaile of Ships, without any viſible occaſion, and the Inſtructions themſelves given by the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151118:60"/>States to their Commanders at Sea; too much cauſe is found to beleeve, that the Lords, the States Generall of the united Provinces, have an intention by force to uſurp the known Right of</hi> England <hi>in the Seas, to deſtroy the Fleets that are (under God) their Walls and Bulwarks, and thereby to expoſe this Commonwealth to Invaſion at their pleaſure, as by their late Action they have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to do: Whereupon the Parliament conceive themſelves obliged to endeavour, with Gods aſſiſtance, as they ſhall have opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſeek Reparation of the wrongs already ſuffered, and Security that the like be not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted for the future. Nevertheleſſe with this mind and deſire, that all differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Nations may (if poſſibly) be friendly and peaceably compoled, as God ſhall open a way by his providence thereunto, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſhall be conducing, to render ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours leſſe dilatory, and more effectuall then thoſe of this kind heretofore uſually have been.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhort and ſmart anſwer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained yet ſomething in it that tended to a poſſibility of an accommodation; yet all the ſeverall conferences and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates about this buſineſſe came to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151118:61"/>but broke quite off,<note place="margin">The Dutch Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours have audience and depart</note> and in ſhort ſpace after the Ambaſſadors had audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in Parliament, took their leaves, and departed.</p>
            <p>And now theſe two mighty States prepare to offend each other, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> the Engliſh Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall, with a gallant and reſolute Fleet of ſhips, advances Northward, towards the Iſles of <hi>Orkney,</hi> to ſeize upon and hinder all ſuch as they ſhould find fiſhing on thoſe coaſts; where he took 12 Dutch men of Warre guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Buſſes, but moſt of the Buſſes were let go.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>George Ayſcue</hi> with his Squadron of Ships being left to guard the narrow Sea,<note place="margin">The Fight between the Dutch and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fleets neer <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
               </note> diſcovered a Fleet of <hi>Flemings</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Calice,</hi> being about 30; of which 10 were taken and burnt, the reſt ran aſhoar on the Coaſts of <hi>France:</hi> Many other Prizes were day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought in (both of the Dutch and French) by the Ships and Frigots of this Commonwealth. Thence Sir <hi>George Ayſcue</hi> with his Fleet ſailed to the Weſtward, to ſeek out the Dutch Fleet, to guard the Seas, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the Merchant-men that lay at
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151118:61"/>
               <hi>Plimouth</hi> through the Channel: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about ſeven or eight Leagues off <hi>Plimouth,</hi> he received intelligence of the Dutch Fleet, and preſently a Councell of Warre was called, upon which they reſolved to ſtand over for the Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> as the moſt probable way to meet with them; and the ſame day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 16. of <hi>Aug.</hi> between one and two in the afternoon, they had ſight of the Dutch Fleet, and preſently made what ſaile they could towards them, to diſcover their number, being about 60 Sail of Men of Warre, and 30 Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantmen: the Engliſh were but 38. ſaile, four Fireſhips, and four Scouts; yet they came up with the enemy about four in the afternoon, and began the fight with much reſolution and gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; Sir <hi>George</hi> and about ſix other Ships charging through the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the enemies Fleet, received much hurt in their Hulls, Maſts, Sails, and Rigging: yet did they tack-about, weather them and charge them all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and continued thus engaged in the body of the enemies Fleet, till it was dark night; and had not the reſt of the Engliſh Captains failed to do their
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151118:62"/>duties, this Dutch Fleet (in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) had been wholly defeated. In this engagement the Engliſh had ſome ſlain and ſome wounded, but of note they loſt only Captain <hi>Pack,</hi> whoſe Leg being ſhot off, he dyed ſoon after of it, who was an honeſt and valiant Seaman: there was wounded Captain <hi>Liſle,</hi> and Captain <hi>Witheridge:</hi> a Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of theirs was ſunk, alſo two other Ships of the enemies were ſuppoſed to be ſunk, but what other loſſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, an accompt could not be had: the darkneſſe of the night put a period to the diſpute,<note place="margin">Both Fleets re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire.</note> ſo that the Dutch ſtood away for the Coaſts of <hi>France,</hi> and the Engliſh for the Port of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> to repair their Maſts and Rigging, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which they could no further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the enemy.</p>
            <p>During this engagement, Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> came from the Northward into the <hi>Downs,</hi> where there fell into his hands about ſix more conſiderable Dutch Prizes, and ſent ſome Frigots to the Weſtward, to reinforce Sir <hi>George Ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcues</hi> Fleet. Preſently after this, Capt. <hi>Penn</hi> with a ſquadron of Ships hover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the Coaſts of <hi>France</hi> ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151118:62"/>ſix Ships more belonging to the Dutch, which had been in the Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> ſervice, and were now returned richly laden, all ſtout Ships of Warre, and of great burthen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sept.</hi> 5. The Engliſh Fleet under Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> riding in the Downs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving intelligence of a French Fleet, weighed Anchor and ſtood over for the French Coaſts; about five of the clock they deſcryed them weighing Anchor in <hi>Calice</hi> road, thinking by that means to eſcape: the night ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, the Engliſh chaſed them as farre as they durſt for the Sands of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> took moſt of them, and about midnight gave over: The Names of thoſe taken were as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Triton</hi> commanded by <hi>Chevalier de Verdiel,</hi> a Ship of 31 Guns, in which was <hi>Monſieur Bimulet,</hi> Commander in Chief of all the Fleet.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Shepheard,</hi> commanded by <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier Boymerant,</hi> of 29 Guus.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gift of God,</hi> commanded by <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier de la Charta,</hi> of 30 Guns.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> commanded by <hi>Monſieur de la Roch,</hi> of 22 Guns.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Creſcent,</hi> commanded by <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151118:63"/>de la Viel Dean,</hi> of 26 Guns.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hunter,</hi> commanded by <hi>Monſieur de la Gicleck,</hi> of 22 Guns.</p>
            <p>The St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> commanded by <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de la Gory,</hi> of 28 Guns.</p>
            <p>A ſmall Frigot of eight Guns.</p>
            <p>Six Fireſhips.</p>
            <p>This French Fleet was bound to touch at <hi>Calice,</hi> there to take in Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Men for the Relief of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk:</hi> but the Engliſh thus intercepting them, the <hi>Dunkirkers</hi> deſpaired of any relief, and yeelded it up to the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards;</hi> the like alſo did <hi>Graveling:</hi> this did in part retaliate for thoſe great loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and injuries the Engliſh had ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sep.</hi> 27.<note place="margin">The Fight between the Dutch and the Engliſh Fleets, called <hi>The Kentiſh knock.</hi>
               </note> Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> with his Fleet, diſcovered on the backſide of <hi>Goodwin Sands,</hi> about 60 ſaile of Dutch men of Warre, under the command of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>De Wit:</hi> on the 28. Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> with his Fleet got under ſaile, and bore in among the enemy, but being upon a Sand called the <hi>Kentiſh Knock</hi> (under which the Dutch placed themſelves, that the Engliſh might be miſchieved if they ſhould endeavour the weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage,) they found they had not three
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151118:63"/>fathom water, inſomuch that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral's Ship, the <hi>Soveraign,</hi> the <hi>Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the <hi>Andrew,</hi> and others, were on ground: but without any harm; they all got preſently off, fell to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe again, and ſtaid by the enemy till night parted: After this diſpute the Dutch abode all night at ſome diſtance to Leeward of the Engliſh, as if they had an intention to engage again. Next morning, <hi>Sep.</hi> 29. at day break, the Dutch Fleet was ſeen about two Leagues Northeaſt of the Engliſh; who (though there was but little wind and various) bore after them all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, but the wind coming to North and B. Weſt, they could not get up to them: yet ſome of the beſt Frigots were commanded to bear up as neer the Dutch as they could, and to keep them in play till the reſt of the Fleet could get up; and with much adoe about three a clock got within ſhot of the enemy, who fearing that by degrees,<note place="margin">The Dutch are ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſted</note> the Engliſh Fleet would get within them, ſet up their main Sailes and ran for it, after whom about ten Frigots had the chaſe till ſix a clock that night. Next morning <hi>Sept.</hi> 30. the Engliſh
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151118:64"/>bore after them again with a freſh gale at S. W. and purſued them untill they had ſight of <hi>Weſt-Gabell</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> and ſaw them run into <hi>Goree.</hi> Hereupon the Engliſh concluded at a Councel of Warre, not to run further upon the Coaſts of <hi>Holland,</hi> as well to avoid the ſhallowes, as becauſe of the want of Proviſion in the Fleet.</p>
            <p>The loſſe that the Dutch apparently ſuſtained was, that three of their Ships were diſabled in the firſt encounter, all their Maſts being cut down, others of them loſt their heads, and others their Boltſprit-maſts, and Yards, the Dutch Rear-Admirall being towed by a Fly-boat of 32 Guns, was boarded by the <hi>None-ſuch</hi> Frigot with 30 men, and the Fly boat with 30 more, but there being water in the Hold, and wanting Maſts and Sails, he took the Rear-Admiral, the Captain and about 80 men out of them, and left the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels with the dead men floating in the Sea. Of the Engliſh, the loſſe was not great, about fortie being ſlain and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout forty wounded; in ſuch ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſort were the Dutch defeated, who were ſo mighty at Sea, that they were
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151118:64"/>a terror to the whole Univerſe.</p>
            <p>The fame of this unhappy breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two ſuch Potent States, quickly ſpread it ſelf into all places, that were any whit eminent for trade or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and the effects thereof were both ſeen and heard in the <hi>Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Sea, as well as in the Engliſh Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, whither the Engliſh had ſent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Ships of Warre, to ſecure their Merchants from the French Pirates of <hi>Toulon, Marſellis,</hi> &amp;c. A ſquadron whereof of four ſaile, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Paragon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Four Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men of Warre are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by eleven Dutch men of Warre in the <hi>Straights.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Phoenix, Conſtant Warwick,</hi> and <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> (having under convoy three Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Ships, two from <hi>Scandarone,</hi> and one from <hi>Smyrna</hi>) met with eleven ſaile of Dutch men of Warre, who preſently came up with the Engliſh, and began the engagement, but night came on and parted them: next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Dutch began again, and found as hot work as can be imagined from ſo ſmall a number, two of their main top-Maſts being ſhot down, and one of their Ships fired,<note place="margin">The <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> Frigot is taken by the Dutch.</note> but afterwards quenched: the <hi>Phoenix</hi> a ſtout Engliſh Frigot of 45 Guns, was clapp'd on board by a heavy Dutch Ship, the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151118:65"/>men overpowered, and the Ship taken. Of this petty ſucceſſe the Dutch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly boaſted: yet they bought it dearly, and that by their number, not their valour; the Engliſh not giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out ſo long as they had men or munition; for the <hi>Paragon</hi> loſt 27 men, and had about 60 wounded; the <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> had but two barrels of Pouder left, ſo hard they ply'd it, and to ſuch ſtreſſe were they put: Yet in deſpight of their Adverſaries, they got ſafe with their Merchants into <hi>Portolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone;</hi> this fight was neer the Iſland of <hi>Corſica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the nick of this breach came into <hi>England</hi> an Ambaſſadour from the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> where he ended his life, before he effected any thing: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother alſo from the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> who being a contemporary, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate with the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> durſt not but dance after their Pipe; and as ſoon as the ghaſtly wound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two States began to feſter, he departed the Land.</p>
            <p>About which time the Parliament (conſidering the condition of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Merchants trading into the Eaſt
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151118:65"/>Countrey, whoſe Ships (to avoid the danger of the Dutch Men of Warre, then in the <hi>Sound</hi>) had put themſelves into the protection of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> but durſt not venture home without a Convoy) ſent a Fleeet of 18 men of Warre, of good force to fetch them home, being in number 22, and laden with ſuch Commodities as the Engliſh had ſpeciall occaſion for, and without which they could not proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the warre with the <hi>Dutch.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly <hi>Sep.</hi> 19. they ſet ſaile out of <hi>Yarmouth</hi> road, and on the 20. they came to an Anchor within two Leagues of <hi>Elſenore</hi> Caſtle; whence the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief ſent a Letter to the Governour of <hi>Elſenore,</hi> by the <hi>Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound</hi> Frigot, and another to the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Admirall, to deſire them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the King with their coming, and for what; with a Letter to the Merchants, and Maſters of the Engliſh Ships at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> to addreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the King, for the ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe of their Ships, then ſhut up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Boomes</hi> at <hi>Copenhagen:</hi> but a mile ſhort of the Caſtle the Ship was ſtopt. Next morning the Captain went up
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151118:66"/>with his Boat, and delivered his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and Letters, which availed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; ſo that another was ſent to the Merchants, and a Meſſenger to the King, but without ſucceſſe; for he could not be admitted to ſpeech with or ſight of him: At length two Lords were ſent to <hi>Elſenore,</hi> unto whom two Engliſh Captains repaired, and urged the reſtoring the Ships; and in ſtead of anſwering to the buſineſſe, they asked, <hi>Why their Ambaſſadour had not audience?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions between the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and King of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Whether they had a Letter from the State of</hi> England <hi>to their King? Why they came ſo boldly upon his Majeſties Streams, and ſo neer his Houſe and Castle, with ſuch a mighty Fleet, without three weeks notice beforehand?</hi> All theſe being impertineut to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, a poſitive anſwer was urged by the Engliſh: and on the 26. of <hi>Sept.</hi> they received a Letter from the King, <hi>That he would ſecure them for the Merchants as carefully as he had done, but would not deliver them to them:</hi> Whereupon the Merchants and Seamen being deſtitute of all hopes of the releaſement of their Ships, left them and came home with this Fleet: who on the 27 of <hi>Sep.</hi> left the <hi>Sound,</hi> and ſteer'd their courſe for
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151118:66"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> and on the laſt of <hi>Sept.</hi> the Admirall of the Fleet, commanded by Capt. <hi>Ball,</hi> ran on ſhoar on the Coaſt of <hi>Shutland,</hi> and was there loſt, but her men ſaved: this Ship carrying the light, it was miraculous that the reſt of the Fleet were not all loſt: this Ship was called the <hi>Antelope,</hi> an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Frigot, and carried above 50 braſs Guns: a little after that they took about 20 Buſſes, a Dutch man of War, and a Freebooter of 20 Guns; and on the 15. of <hi>Octob.</hi> arrived ſafe in <hi>Burling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Bay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after this an Agent, by name <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> was ſent to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if yet by fair means they could obtain their deſires; but in vain: for he did not only detain the Ships, but at length unladed them, and ſold the Goods. Which incivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities towards thoſe that never injured him in the leaſt, but deſired by all fair means, to enter into Amity with him, may one day (by the good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God) be requited and aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> (drunk with rage, and greedy of revenge for thoſe rubs
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151118:67"/>the Engliſh had lately given them, and for the continuall loſſe of their Ships dayly ſurprized and in great numbers brought into our Channel) uſed their utmoſt care and induſtry in rigging and ſetting forth their Fleet: which (notwithſtanding the ſeaſon of the year) they effected; and <hi>Decemb.</hi> 20. they appeared on the backſide of the <hi>Goodwin-Sands,</hi> being 90 men of Warre, and 10 Fireſhips; the Engliſh under Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> were but 42, and not half of them mann'd, moſt of the beſt Ships being laid up when there was moſt need of them: which default (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt) was cauſed through the improvident, treacherous, finiſter and ſlothfull actings of ſuch as then ſteer'd the helme of this State, whom God (in his due time) will bring to a rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning for their miſcarriages. The Engliſh notwithſtanding the paucity of their number,<note place="margin">The Dutch &amp; Engliſh engage, and the Engliſh are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</note> reſolved to go out and ſight them: and <hi>Novemb.</hi> 30. being fair weather, both Fleets plyed to the Weſtward, and about eleven of the clock that day were both engaged, the Engliſh having got the Weather-gage: in this ſight half of the Engliſh Fleet
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151118:67"/>(as ſmall as it was) came not up, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending want of Men, inſomuch that a few Ships of the Engliſh bore the brunt of that fight with the whole Fleet of the Dutch; the Vanguard, and the <hi>Victory</hi> engaging with 20 of the Dutch from firſt to laſt, and yet got clear of them all.<note place="margin">The <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Bonadven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> are taken.</note> In the evening the <hi>Garland,</hi> an Engliſh Ship of above 40 Guns, was boarded by two Dutch Flag-ſhips, and after ſhe had blown up her Decks, for want of men was taken. The <hi>Bonadventure</hi> (a Merchants Ship) attempting to relieve the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was boarded, yet cleer'd her decks ſeverall times, the Captain whereof being ſlain, the Ship was at length ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> going in the <hi>Triumph</hi> to relieve the <hi>Garland,</hi> had his foretop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſt ſhot by the board, was twice boarded, and yet got off ſafe, as did all the reſt, except the two aforementioned, which though they fetcht not farre, yet dearly bought: two other Ships likewiſe fell into the hands of the Dutch preſently after the Fight, but both Merchants Ships. General <hi>Blake</hi> upon this, with his Fleet withdrew in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Lee</hi> Road, to be reinforced with
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151118:68"/>Ships and Men. This Victory, ſuch as you have heard, made the Dutch great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoyce and inſult; ſuch is the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and levity of thoſe which gaze on the meer outſide of things, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves at firſt view: Nay by their Ambaſſadors they made the news thereof to eccho in moſt of the Princes Courts in <hi>Chriſtendome: Mirum qutem quantum fama popular is addidit fabulae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Engliſh like a Bear robbed of her whelps, and awakened at this ſudden eclipſe of their glory, ſplendor, and wonted valour, betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to new reſolutions, for the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out a conſiderable Fleet, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to allay the ſoaring pride of their adverſaries, and to ſtifle thoſe unruly clamours and generall diſcontents of the people every where murmuring and inveighing againſt their Governours, as if they had (by ſecret and clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine deſigns) contrived the ruine of the Nation by a deſtruction of the Fleet.</p>
            <p>And firſt they took into conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what due encouragement was fit to be given to Mariners and Seamen: and ordered,</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:151118:68"/>
            <p>That the Wages of every able Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, fit for the Helme and Head, Top and Yard, ſhould be advanced from 18. <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> the moneth, to 23. <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> the moneth, and all the reſt proportionable.</p>
            <p>That for every Prize they ſhal take, and ſhall ſo be adjudged in the Court of Admiralty, they ſhall have ten Shillings for every Tun the ſaid Ship ſhal mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and ſix Pounds ten Shillings four Pence for every peece of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, whether Iron or braſſe, to be ſhared and divided amongſt them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably, according to their places and Offices in the Ship: and that they ſhall have all Pillage they ſhall find up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or above the Gun-deck of any ſuch Prize.</p>
            <p>That they ſhall have ten Pounds a Gun, for every man of Warre they ſhall ſink or deſtroy, by Fire or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to be divided as aforeſaid, with a moneths <hi>gratis</hi> money to all that ſhal voluntarily come into their Service within fortie dayes.</p>
            <p>That for ſupplying of neceſſary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions unto ſick and wounded men aboard, there be allowed five pounds for ſix moneths ſervice for every hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151118:69"/>men. That care be taken upon their diſcharge for the payment of their Tickets and Conduct mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>That a covenient houſe be provided in or neer <hi>Dover, Deale,</hi> or <hi>Sandwitch,</hi> as an Hoſpitall for the accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch wounded men, as ſhall be there ſet on ſhoare. Theſe with ſeverall other branches of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were printed and publiſhed, to the great ſatisfaction of the Seamen: inſomuch that towards the latter end of <hi>February,</hi> 1653. the Engliſh had a brave and reſolute Fleet out at Sea; notwithſtanding all the care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> to hinder all Nations from bringing any Pitch, Tarre or Maſts into this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Febru.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and Dutch Fleets en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage neer the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> and <hi>Portland.</hi>
               </note> 18. The Dutch Fleet in number about 80, with about 150 Merchantmen from <hi>Roan, Nants,</hi> and <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> were diſcovered between the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> and <hi>Portland:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 8 in the morning, the headmoſt of the Engliſh Fleet came up and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Triumph,</hi> where was Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> and Gen. <hi>Dean,</hi> with three
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151118:69"/>or four more; the reſt were not able to get up, being to the Leeward: ſo that them few were conſtrained to bear the firſt brunt, holding play with no leſſe then 30 of the Dutch men of War, and thus it continued till two a clock in the afternoon; after which about about half the Engliſh Fleet came up, and engaged the Dutch till the night parted. In this fight the Engliſh loſt none ſave the <hi>Sampſon,</hi> a Dutch Prize, which being made unſerviceable, was ſunk by themſelves, the men being all taken out and ſaved, which Ship firſt ſunk the enemy that maimed her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Febr.</hi> 19. The Engliſh made towards the Dutch, and followed them upon the chace a good while, in which days ſervice ſome of the enemies Ships were brought by the Lee and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Febr.</hi> 20. They Engaged the Dutch again, and the diſpute grew hot, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the enemy began to fire out of their ſternmoſt Ports, and make away, ſo that divers of their Merchants Ships ſell into the hands of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: At evening the Engliſh Fleet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt <hi>Bolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and not
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151118:70"/>farre from the ſhore, the wind at <hi>N. N.</hi> Weſt, which was bad for them to get to their own ſhoare; they endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by haling upon a tack, to get <hi>Dover</hi> Road; but many of their Ships ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Sails and Rigging much tattered and torn, they came to an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh in this fight took about 50 Merchants, and nine men of Warre, ſeverall of their men of Warre were likewiſe ſunk by the Engliſh, beſide what the enemy themſelves ſunk that were made unſerviceable, and by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters out of <hi>France,</hi> it was certified alſo that above 2000 dead bodies of the Dutch were ſeen upon the French ſhores. Preſently after this hot and terrible fight, there was 1500 taken Priſoners and brought to <hi>London.</hi> Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> was wounded in this engagement, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Commanders of the Engliſh, of eminent worth and gallantry, were ſlain and wounded alſo. Now though a particular accompt of the Dutch loſs could never yet be fully known, yet without all queſtion, it was as ſad and dreadfull a loſſe to that State, as they ever yet knew, for which let Gods
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151118:70"/>Name alone be magnified: and though I am none of thoſe, <hi>Qui malis gaudeo alienis,</hi> yet ſeeing (that by a kind of fatal neceſſity) the ſtroaks of adverſe fortune muſt fall heavy ſomewhere, we ought with hands lifted up, to bleſſe God for our deliverance.</p>
            <p>The Dutch being deeply ſenſible of this loſſe, ſent a Letter to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> yet ſigned only by the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt Frieſland:</hi> in anſwer to which, the Parliament ſent a Letter, ſignifying their deſire of a friendly compliance, for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding the further ſhedding of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian bloud, but nothing came there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>But leſt the Engliſh ſhould ſurfet with exceſſe of joy for their late Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories over their enemies; God was pleaſed to give them a check, by an unexpected defeat of their Ships in the Levant-Seas, which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh (having by a ſtratagem regained the <hi>Phoenix</hi> Frigot from the Dutch as ſhe lay in <hi>Leverne Mole</hi>) fitted themſelves for another encounter with the Dutch? Capt. <hi>Badiley</hi> with nine
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151118:71"/>men of Warre,<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fleet in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Seas, are again worſted by the Dutch.</note> weighed out of <hi>Porto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longone,</hi> towards the relief of thoſe other Ships under Capt. <hi>Apleton,</hi> that lay in <hi>Levorne Mole,</hi> and for ſeverall moneths had been cooped up by 22 men of Warre; hereupon the Engliſh Ships under Capt. <hi>Apleton</hi> weighed out of the <hi>Mole,</hi> a little ſooner then they ſhould have done, and were preſently engaged by the whole Fleet of the Dutch, who having the advantage of the wind, with their Admirall and two other Ships, clapt the <hi>Leopard</hi> aboard, a ſtout Engliſh Ship of above fiftie Guns, who bravely maintained the fight above five hours againſt them all, till at length being overborne by the number of the enemy, ſhe was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bonadventure</hi> by a ſhot in her Pouder room, took fire and was blown up.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Peregrine</hi> was engaged with foun or five of the Dutch at a time, and having her main-Maſt, and miſen-Maſt ſhot away, and being overpowered with number was taken.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Levant-Merchant</hi> was firſt board<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one of the enemies Ships of 36
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151118:71"/>Guns, and (after two hours fight) by another as big; the firſt of which ſunk preſently after; yet was ſhe alſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt by the Dutch.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sampſon</hi> was boarded by young <hi>Trump,</hi> Rear Amirall of the Dutch on one ſide, and by a fire-Ship on the other, ſo that ſhe was quickly fired.</p>
            <p>Some there were that did not ſtick to traduce Capt. <hi>Badiley</hi> and thoſe with him, as if he had been wanting in point of duty, toward the relief of the Ships aforeſaid: when as they were all well nigh deſtroyed, before he could poſſibly come up. Where when he had done what in him lay, and ſeeing his Fleet in ſuch a hazardous condition, like a wiſe Commander, made all the ſail he could away, for preſervation of that part of the Fleet; and this he hath ſo clearly proved, that he is wholly acquitted from having any hand in that miſcarriage.</p>
            <p>The Relation wherein this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth ſtood with the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations was in this ſort.<note place="margin">The King of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall</hi> and the State of <hi>England</hi> conclude a peace.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Portugall</hi> not able to reſiſt ſo powerfull a State as this (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more then enough to do, to grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151118:72"/>with the wealthy Spaniard) ſent over an Ambaſſadour extraordinary, with a ſumptuous train of followers, to conclude a Peace with the Engliſh; who (after many conferences, frequent addreſſes, and large offers made) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the ſame; yet to this day he hath not fully fiuiſhed his Negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo as to ſatisfie the Merchants for their great loſſes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>France</hi> the Engliſh were court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by two Parties:<note place="margin">A French Agent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives at <hi>London.</hi>
               </note> by an Agent from the King of <hi>France,</hi> deſiring a releaſe of his Ships taken (as aforeſaid) going to the relief of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> as alſo that there might be a right underſtanding between the two Nations. And by four Deputies from the Prince of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> arive at <hi>London</hi> alſo.</note> craving aid againſt the Cardinall and his creatures, who had ſtraightly beſieged the City of <hi>Bourdeaux:</hi> all which Negotiations were ineffectuall, for alas the breach was too high be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Nations to be eaſily ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</p>
            <p>Other Nations by Letters and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe endeavoured to be mediators and compoſers of thoſe mortal jarres that were between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:151118:72"/>as the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> the Cantons of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> the Imperiall Cities of <hi>Lubeck</hi> and <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This was the poſture of the Civill and Military affairs of this Nation, when his Excellency the Lord General <hi>Cromwell</hi> (a man as it were by Divine appointment ſet apart for great enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes) perceiving the notorious cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, dilatory proceedings, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious and arbitrary actings of the Parliament, to perpetuate their ſeſſion, and to inthrall the people (by defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and disfranchiſing them of their antient and undoubted Liberties of equall and ſucceſſive Repreſentatives) entred the Parliament Houſe, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome of his principall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and there delivered certain rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why a period ought to be put to that Parliament;<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is diſſolved.</note> which was preſently done, the Speaker with the reſt of the Members (ſome by force, ſome through fear, and ſome murmuring) departed the Houſe. For which dyſaſter no man moved either tongue or hand in their behalf, it being generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, that though the Nation poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly might not be bettered by this
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151118:73"/>change, yet a worſe could not befall it. And thus was this mighty Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell diſſolved, their Powers transferred into the hands of the Souldiery, and their Names reproacht and vilified with the ſcorns and dirigies of the common people, who being well pleaſed with the doing thereof, enquired not into the reaſons or cauſes why it was done. But to ſatisfie the wiſer ſort, and thoſe that were more curious enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers into the true and genuine cauſes of things, Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Councell of Officers publiſhed a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, the ſubſtance whereof was as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>THat after God was pleaſed marvellouſly to appear for his people,<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Councel of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note> in reducing <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſo great a degree of peace, and <hi>England</hi> to perfect quiet; whereby the Parliament had opportunity to give the people the harveſt of all their labour, bloud and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and to ſettle a due Liberty in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Civil and Spirituall things: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they were obliged by their duty, engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and thoſe great and wonderful things God hath wrought for them. But they made
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151118:73"/>ſo little progreſſe therein that it was matter of much grief to the good people of the Land; who thereupon applyed themſelves to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, expecting redreſſe by their means, who (though unwilling to meddle with the Civill Authority) agreed that ſuch Officers as were Members of Parliament ſhould move them to proceed vigorouſly, in reforming what was amiſſe in the Commonwealth, and in ſetling it upon a foundation of Juſtice and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which being done, it was hoped the Parliament would have anſwered their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations.</p>
                  <p>But finding the contrary, they renewed their deſires by an humble Petition in <hi>Aug. 1652.</hi> which produced no conſiderable effect, nor was any ſuch progreſſe made therein, as might imply their reall intentions to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh what was petitioned for; but rather an averſneſſe to the things themſelves, with much bitterneſſe and oppoſition to the people of God and his Spirit acting in them: in ſo much that the godly Party in Parliament were rendred of no further uſe, then to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the ends of a corrupt Party, for ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting their deſires of perpetuating themſelves in the ſupreame Government.</p>
                  <p>For obviating theſe evils, the Officers of the Army obtained ſeverall meetings with
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151118:74"/>ſome of the Parliament, to conſider what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy might be applyed to prevent the ſame; but ſuch endeavours proving ineffectuall, it became evident, that this Parliament, through the corruption of ſome, the jealouſie of others, the non-attendance of many, would never anſwer thoſe ends which God, his People, and the whole Nation expected from them; But that this cauſe which God had ſo greatly bleſſed, muſt needs languiſh under their hands, and by degrees be loſt; and the Lives, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Comforts of his people be delivered into their enemies hands.</p>
                  <p>All which being ſadly and ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the honeſt people of the Nation as well as by the Army, it ſeemed a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon us, who had ſeen ſo much of the power and preſence of God, to conſider of ſome effectuall means whereby to eſtabliſh righteouſneſſe and peace in theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>And after much debate it was judged ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that the ſupreame Government ſhould be by the Parliament devolved upon known perſons fearing God, and of approved integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for a time, as the moſt hopefull way to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance all Gods people, reform the Law, and adminiſter Juſtice impartially: hoping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the people might forget Monarchy, and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151118:74"/>underſtand their true intereſt in the election of ſucceſſive Parliaments; that ſo the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment might be ſetled upon a right Baſis, without hazard to this glorious cauſe, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitating to keep up Armies for the defence of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>And being ſtill reſolved to uſe all means poſſibly to avoid extraordinary courſes, we prevailed with about twenty Members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to give us a conference, with whom we plainly debated the neceſſity and juſtneſſe of our Propoſals: The which found no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, but in ſtead thereof it was offered that the way was to continue ſtill this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as being that from which we might probably expect all good things. This being vehemently inſiſted on did much confirm us in our apprehenſions; That not any love to a Repreſentative, but the making uſe thereof to recruit, and ſo to perpetuate themſelves, was their aim, in the Act they had then under conſideration.</p>
                  <p>For preventing the conſummating whereof, and all the ſad and evil conſequences, which upon the grounds aforeſaid muſt have enſued, and whereby at one blow the intereſt of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men and of this glorious cauſe had been endangered to be laid in the duſt, and theſe Nations embroyled in new troubles, at a time
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:151118:75"/>when our enemies abroad are watching all advantages againſt, and ſome of them actually engaged in Warre with us; we have been neceſſitated (though with much reluctancy) to put an end to this Parliament.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Declaration and proceedings of General <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Councell of Officers, was attended with the conſent of the Generals and all the Captains of the Fleet, as alſo of the Generals and Officers of all the land Forces in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaſt the Magiſtrates, and other publick Miniſters of the Nation, ſhould be ſtartled at this ſudden change, ſo as to ſwerve from their duties; or others ſhould take occaſion thereby to make diſturbances in the Commonwealth, this following Declaration, was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>WHereas the Parliament being diſſolved, perſons of approved fidelity and honeſty, are (according to the late Declaration of the <hi>22.</hi> of <hi>April</hi> laſt) to be called from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parts of this Commonwealth to the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151118:75"/>ſupreame Authority; and although effectuall proceedings are and have been had for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting thoſe reſolutions, yet ſome convenient time being required for the aſsembling of thoſe perſons, it hath been found neceſſary for preventing the miſchiefs and inconveniences which may ariſe in the mean while to the publike affairs, that a Councell of State be conſtituted, to take care of and intend, the peace, ſafety and preſent management of the affairs of this Commonwealth: which being ſetled accordingly, the ſame is hereby declared and publiſhed, to the end all perſons may take notice thereof, and in their ſever all places and ſtations, demean themſelves peaceably, giving obedience to the Laws of the Nation as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore: in the exerciſe and adminiſtration whereof, as endeavours ſhall be uſed, that no oppreſſion or wrong be done to the people, ſo a strict accompt will be required, of all ſuch as ſhall do any thing to endanger the publike peace and quiet, upon any pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Aprill. 30. 1653.</hi>
                     </date>
                     <signed>O. Cromwell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:151118:76"/>
            <p>Theſe Domeſtick revolutions did in ſome meaſure heighten the ſpirits of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who thought that ſome eminent diſtractions and commotions (both by ſea and land) would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon enſue: but they were much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; for the Maritime affairs of theſe Nations (wherein the woe or weal thereof conſiſted) were carryed on with as much dexterity, policy, and ſpeed, as the neceſſity and urgency of the occaſion did require.</p>
            <p>Now the Dutch having a great Fleet of Merchants Ships outward bound, durſt not adventure through the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel; but with a Fleet of about 90 Men of Warre, conducted them by the North of <hi>Scotland</hi> towards the <hi>Sound,</hi> and there met with another Fleet of their Merchant men homewards bound, ſome from <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> ſome from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and ſome from <hi>France:</hi> all which they conveyed home in ſafety, not having met with the Engliſh Fleet either going or coming: which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done, and hearing that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fleet was to the Northwards, they ſet ſail with their Fleet, and came into the <hi>Downs,</hi> where they took two or
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:151118:76"/>three ſmall Veſſels, and made ſeverall ſhot into the Town of <hi>Dover,</hi> with which bravadoes they greatly delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves, and boaſted that the Engliſh Fleet was loſt, that Hue and Cry muſt be ſent after them, and ſuch like ſpeeches they vented and vaunted with: when on a ſudden the Engliſh Fleet arrived from the Northwards, and on the 28 of <hi>May,</hi> came into <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> Road. <hi>June.</hi> 1. Being at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor in <hi>Sole Bay,</hi> they diſcovered two Dutch galliot Hoyes, to which chaſe was given till the whole Fleet was diſcovered, but the weather proving dark, they loſt fight of them. <hi>June.</hi> 3. The Engliſh Fleet (being at anchor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the South head of the <hi>Gober</hi>) diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the Enemy about two Leagues to Leeward, being about 100 ſail:<note place="margin">The Fight between the Dutch and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fleets off the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreland.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Engliſh weighed and made ſail towards them; between eleven and twelve at noon both Fleets were engaged, and for ſome hours the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute was ſharp, inſomuch that about ſix a clock in the evening the enemy bore right away before the wind, little more being done that night. Next morning early the Engliſh were
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151118:77"/>fair by the Dutch again;<note place="margin">The Dutch are worſted, and many of their Ships ſunk and taken.</note> but there being little wind, it was noon ere they could engage them, and after four hours diſpute, the Dutch endeavoured as faſt as they could to get away; but the wind freſhing Weſtwardly, the Engliſh bore in ſo hard among them, that they took eleven Men of Warre, and two water-Hoyes, ſix Captains, 1500 Priſoners, and ſunk ſix Men of Warre more; the reſt of the Dutch Fleet (if night had not prevented) would probably have been cut off; but darkneſſe coming on and being neer the Flats, and neceſſitated to ſtay and mend their Sails and Rigging which were much ſhattered and torn, they came to an Anchor about ten a clock that night. The loſſe which the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſuſtained in this fight, was of Gen. <hi>Dean</hi> one of their Admirals, who with a great ſhot was taken off the firſt days engagement; one Captain they loſt beſide, they had ſlain at the uttermoſt not above 150 men, and about 240 wounded, but they loſt not one Ship. That which greatly animated the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and diſcouraged the Dutch, was the opportune and ſeaſonable coming
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:151118:77"/>in of Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> with about 16 ſail of ſtout Men of Warre. The Dutch ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (by the advantage of the night) got into the <hi>Wielings,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lye</hi> and the <hi>Texel;</hi> the Engliſh called a Councell of all the Captains of the Fleet, to adviſe what was the moſt convenient courſe for improvement of the victory to the beſt advantage: where it was reſolved to make what ſail they could with the whole Fleet towards the <hi>Wiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> ſo far as with ſafety they might, and ſo range the Dutch Coaſt till they came to the <hi>Texel,</hi> where they lay for a pretty ſpace of time, taking Prizes continually more or leſſe, to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prejudice of the Dutch, whoſe Ships could in that while neither go out nor come in, nor get together in any one Port, whereby to unite and get to a head; in which condition, I ſhal for the preſent leave them.</p>
            <p>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Councell of Officers having finiſhed their conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and reſolutions about thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to whom the Legiſlative Power of the Nation was to be committed; War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants were iſſued out to each perſon ſo choſen in the three Nations, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:151118:78"/>at the Councel-Chamber at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, July,</hi> 4. 1653. a Copy whereof followes.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>FOr as much as upon the diſſolution of the late Parliament it became neceſſary, that the peace, ſafety and good government of this Commonwealth ſhould be provided for; and in order thereunto, divers perſons ſearing God, and of approved fidelity and honeſty, are by my ſelf, with the advice of my Councel of Officers nominated; to whom the great charge and truſt of ſo weighty affairs is to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And having good aſſurance of your love to, and courage for God, and the Intereſt of his Cauſe, and the good people of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth.</p>
                  <p>I <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> Captain Generall and Commander in chief of all the Armies and Forces raiſed and to be raiſed within this Commonwealth, do hereby ſummon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you (being of the Perſons nominated) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally to be and appear at the Councel-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber commonly known or called by the name of the Councel-chamber at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> within the City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> upon the <hi>4</hi> day of <hi>July</hi> next enſuing the date hereof, and then and there to take upon you the ſaid truſt, unto which you are hereby called and appointed to ſerve as a Member for the County of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:151118:78"/>And hereof you are not to faile.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given under my hand and Seal <date>the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> day of <hi>June, 1653.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>O. Cromwell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 4. The ſeverall Members met accordingly in the Councel-Chamber, where was the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and many of his Officers about him, who ſtanding up, made an excellent, uſefull and ſeaſonable Speech unto them; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting the many wonderfull mercies of God towards this Nation, and the continued ſeries of providences, by which he had appeared, in carrying on this Cauſe, and bringing affairs into the preſent condition.</p>
            <p>He ſet forth likewiſe the progreſſe of affairs ſince the famous victory at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> as alſo the actings of the Army thereupon, after divers applications to the Parliament, and much waiting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, with the grounds and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their diſſolving the late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he declared to be for the preſervation of this Cauſe, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of all honeſt men who have been engaged therein.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:151118:79"/>
            <p>He in like manner held forth the cleerneſſe of the call given to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers then preſent, to take upon them the ſupreme Authority: and from the Scriptures exhorted them to their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and encouraged them therein. He further defired them that a tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe might be uſed towards all conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious perſons of what judgement ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>Which having ended, his Excellency produced an Inſtrument under his own hand and Seal, whereby he did with the advice of his Officers, devolve and intruſt the Supreme Authority and Government of this Commonwealth, into the hands of the Perſons there met: Who, or any forty of them, are to be held and acknowledged the Supreme Authority of the Nation; unto whom all perſons within the ſame, and the territories thereunto belonging, are to yeeld obedience and ſubjection. And that they ſit no longer then the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1654. And three moneths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thein diſſolution, they were to make choice of other Perſons to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them, who were not to ſit above a twelvemoneth, and then to take care
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:151118:79"/>for a ſucceſſion in Government. Which Inſtrument being delivered to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, his Lordſhip commended them to God, and with his Officers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew. From thence the Members ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed forthwith to the old Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſe, and there ſate <hi>de die in diem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time <hi>John Lilburne</hi> (of whom I have already made mention) being a few moneths before baniſhed the Land, by an Act of the foregoing Parliament, for certain crimes laid to his charge; took occaſion upon this change of Government to come into <hi>England,</hi> and caſt himſelf upon his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> craving his protection in ſeveral pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick addreſſes; who unwilling to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe or meddle with affairs of that nature, left him to the Law: in ſomuch that he was commited to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and the next Seſſions or Gaol-delivery,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> tried at the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the <hi>Old Baily.</hi>
               </note> he was brought to triall in the <hi>Old-Baily, July</hi> 13. but nothing was done that day, ſave that Councell was aſſigned him according to his demand. <hi>July,</hi> 14. he was again brought to the Barre, but refuſed to put in his Plea, unleſs
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:151118:80"/>he might have a copy of his Indictment; which was at length granted him. <hi>July</hi> 15. he appeared at the Barre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but little was done that day. <hi>July</hi> 16. he appeared and delivered in divers Exceptions to the Bill of Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which were ſigned by his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and received by the Court; which day the Seſſions ended, ſo that the buſineſſe was put off to the next Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. <hi>Aug.</hi> 13. he appeared before the Bench again, and put in an Exception, demanding an Oyer of the Judgement given againſt him in Parliament, as well as of the Act grounded thereupon. <hi>Aug.</hi> 16. he appeared again, the Point argued on both ſides, but nothing more was done that day. <hi>Aug.</hi> 20. he was again brought before the Court, where he joyned iſſue, and pleaded not guilty; whereupon a Jury was impan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel'd, and Witneſſes examined to make good the Charge; as alſo Witneſſes on the behalf of the Priſoner, who in making his defence, held the Court ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall hours; and in anſwer thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Councel for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth were alſo heard. The Jury ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Charge, after hearing the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:151118:80"/>whole buſineſſe withdrew,<note place="margin">Is quitted, by the Jury.</note> and about twelve of the clock that night deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up their Verdict, That they found him Not guilty: whereupon he was ſent back to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and ſoon after was from thence ſent to the Tower, where he yet remains.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what endeavours were uſed to rid the Nation of this incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable fellow, by Tryals, Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and what not? but hitherto in vain; when as many a gallant Heart farre tranſcending him in birth and parts, have fallen by the ſword of Juſtice, in the twinkling of an eye: But it may be God hath reſerved him to be a greater plague to this Nation, whoſe heart I fear is the ſeed-plot of ſedition and diviſion. True it is, he is a man of a penetrating judgement, quick wit, and voluble tongue, bold and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in all his undertakings: he is likewiſe peeviſh and paſſionate out of meaſure; affects popularity, and is of an implacable ſpirit, not to be appeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but with the bloud of his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: Nor can I deny but ſome of thoſe things he aimed at were honeſt, and uſefull for the people, but he ſteered
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:151118:81"/>not the right courſe to attain thoſe ends.</p>
            <p>The condition of the Engliſh affairs in <hi>Scotland</hi> was now much after this ſort;<note place="margin">The ſtate of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> although the Engliſh had got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their poſſeſſion moſt or all of the ſtrong Towns, Forts, and Caſtles in the Lowlands, yet many incurſions were made thereinto by the Highland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſuch like looſe and barbarous people, committing many outrages, ſpoils and cruell murthers upon the people and ſouldiers in ſtragling par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and forthwith would betake themſelves to ſuch inacceſſible faſtneſſes, that they could not be purſued: The like they do yet daily in great numbers, and are headed by <hi>Glencarne, Atholl, Seafort</hi> and others; the laſt of which was ſo bold as to ſend a Summons to a Ship that lay at Anchor at <hi>Lewis</hi> Iſland, (having before ſurprized ſeven or eight men that went aſhore for Proviſions) which Summons is as followes.</p>
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:151118:81"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Copy of the Summons.</head>
                  <p>BEing incited, not only by Conſcience and Honour, to ſtand firm to the Principles of Loyalty; but alſo diſdaining even in rational intereſt, to ſtoop to ſuch a wavering and ſervile Power as now Ruleth; I have laid hold on thoſe men come aſhore, as promoving the ſame: Wherefore I ſummon you to deliver your Veſſel for his Majeſties ſervice; and being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly perſwaded, that all or moſt part of you are with grief of heart employed in ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; I do aſſure all that will voluntarily ſhun the unneceſſary effuſion of bloud, by that ſurrender, ſhall have ſuch fair quarter as is ſitting for me to grant, and as your ſeveral conditions do require, and according to your demeanours herein, you may expect to find me your Friend accordingly.</p>
                  <trailer>For the Captain, Souldiers, Maſter, and Mariners of the <hi>Fortune,</hi> Theſe.</trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Seafort.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The affairs of <hi>Ireland</hi> were much after the ſame paſſe:<note place="margin">The ſtate of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </note> for the Engliſh having reduced all the ſtrong holds of that
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:151118:82"/>Country, and ſhipt away moſt of thoſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels that (according to Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) came in by ſuch a time, for <hi>Spain</hi> and other parts; except ſuch as were found guilty of the maſſacre of the Proteſtants at the firſt rebellion, who were in ſeverall places of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion tryed, condemned and executed, in great numbers, drave the reſt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> into the Province of <hi>Conaught,</hi> and fell to approportion out the Land of the other three Provinces, for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Adventurers, and of the arrears of the Souldiery; but are in ſome meaſure ſtill moleſted by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laws of that Nation, the <hi>Tories,</hi> Coſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>germans to the ancient <hi>Picts,</hi> and <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhanks</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the <hi>Banditi</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> (perceiving that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was to be got of the Engliſh but blowes, and ſenſible of their great loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) ſent four Commiſſioners into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to ſet on foot the Treaty again, <hi>viz. Monſteur Bevering, Newport, Younſtall,</hi> and <hi>Vanderparre,</hi> who ſoon after his arrivall departed this life: the reſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued their negotiations ſo cloſe, that we are not left altogether without
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:151118:82"/>hopes of an accommodation. Yet did not this Treaty produce either a ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any intermiſſion of Arms; but all manner of hoſtility was exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on both fides, as appeared by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remarkable fight between the two Fleets during the Treaty, which it is like much quickned the ſame, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner whereof was thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 29. The Engliſh Scouts diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered a Dutch Fleet from the <hi>Wielings,</hi> of about 95 ſaile of Men of Warre, upon which the Engliſh Fleet made what ſaile they could after them, which the enemy diſcerning ſtood away; yet by five a clock that evening, ſome of the Engliſh Frigots engaged them, and ſoon after 30 Ships or thereabouts got up and engaged, the reſt of the Fleet being a ſtern; thoſe ſew bearing the whole brunt of that dayes fight, till night came, and forced both Fleets to retire: the Dutch were ſo ply'd in this firſt dayes engagement, that they were diſcovered to ſend away ſome of their maimed Ships in the night, and with their whole Fleet got by, ſtriving to make a conjunction with 25 ſail of ſtout Ships they expected out of the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:151118:83"/>
               <hi>Texel;</hi> which by plying up towards them (undiſcerned by the Engliſh) they obtained: which conjunction the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh (by reaſon of thick and foul wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) could not hinder by engagement, nor otherwiſe.<note place="margin">The Dutch &amp; Engliſh Fleets en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage.</note> Next morning the Dutch with their new recruits, fell upon the Engliſh Fleet in a gallant poſture, and fought courageouſly from five a clock in the morning, till one in the afternoon, both Fleets paſſing through each other with much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, endeavouring to burn, fink, and deſtroy one another, as if the whole buſineſſe ſhould have been decided by the event of this battell: yet the Dutch never went off, but with the loſſe of ſome of their Ships, which were either ſunk or burnt: The <hi>Garland</hi> a ſtour Man of Warre (which the Dutch had formerly taken from the Engliſh) was laid aboard by the <hi>Worceſter</hi> Frigot and burnt: The <hi>Triumph</hi> and the <hi>Andrew</hi> were clapt aboard by two or three Dutch fireſhips, and received ſome hurt in their ſails, but were quickly cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them, by the valour and induſtry of ſome particular men. The Dutch ſeeing themſelves in a declining po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:151118:83"/>many of their Ships being ſunk and burnt,<note place="margin">The Dutch are put to ſlight, and many of their ſhips ſunk.</note> and unwilling to abide a further hazard (their ſpirits being daunted) began to bear away with all the ſail they could make, and made directly for the <hi>Texel;</hi> ſo that it was not thought convenient by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, to be too bold with the ſhore, not knowing how the wind might take them, many of their Ships being diſabled; but one or two ſmall Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Veſſels kept fight of them till morning, and ſaw them ſteer into the <hi>Texel</hi> Harbour, having Boats with lights to ſhew them the way in. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Engliſh at a Councel of War, reſolved that the whole Fleet ſhould ſet ſail for <hi>Sole-Bay,</hi> to diſpoſe of ſuch Ships as were diſabled, as alſo of their wounded men, and Priſoners. The loſſe which the Engliſh received at this fight, was as followes. 300 Men were ſlain outright, whereof ſeaven Captains, <hi>Graves, Chapman, Taylor, New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Criſp, Owen, Cox,</hi> and Captain <hi>Peacock:</hi> they had alſo 700 wounded, of which five Captains, <hi>Stokes, Seaman, Rous, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Cubit.</hi> The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular loſſe which the Dutch received,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:151118:84"/>as to the number and quality of thoſe that were ſlain or wounded, came not to our knowledge: but the viſible loſſe they had, was of about 30 Men of Warre ſunk and fired; their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Lord Admirall <hi>Van-Trump</hi> was ſlain in the midſt of the engagement: and out of the Dutch Ships, that lay ſinking in the Sea, the Engliſh took out ſix Captains, and about a thouſand other Priſoners. This was the ſaddeſt conflict that hath hapned between the two Republicks, but a moſt ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble victory to the Engliſh, who I hope will not fail to make a good improvement thereof. For this piece of ſervice, the Parliament ordered that Gold Chains ſhould be given to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall <hi>Blake</hi> and <hi>Monke,</hi> as a mark of their favour, as alſo to Vice-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Pen,</hi> and Rear-Admirall <hi>Lawſon;</hi> other Chains were ordered to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the other Flag-Captains, and Medals of Silver to the Officers of the Fleet. It was afterwards known by Letters out of <hi>Holland,</hi> that the Dutch loft about 6000 Men in this engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:151118:84"/>
            <p>And now Reader (having brought thee well-nigh to the period of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and hitherto entertained thee with the relation of things meerly Civil and Military) I ſhall (according to my skill) give thee ſome accompt of the ſtate of Religion, for theſe few years laſt paſt, which was ſuch and in ſo many ſhapes, that no one form can be aſſigned thereto: for in ſtead of an abſolute conformity in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, there was a generall non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; Hereſies being daily broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in every corner of the Land, which continually ſprung up like <hi>Hydra's</hi> heads, one upon the neck of another, by which means the minds of the people became unſetled and ſhaken in the Principles of Faith and Doctrine; each particular faction tracing a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent track to find the truth, when as indeed, there is but one way, and one truth; the numbers and names where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of if I ſhould undertake to give you, I might reckon <hi>ad infinitum:</hi> viz. Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, Anabaptiſts, and thoſe of ſeverall kinds; ſome for Impoſition of hands, anointing with Oyl, and waſhing of feet; and ſome againſt them.
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:151118:85"/>Browniſts, Millenaries, Arminians, Socinians, Adamites, Diggers, Seekers, Shakers, Ranters, Enthuſiaſts, Arians, Pelagians, <hi>cum multis aliis:</hi> of all which I ſhall ſay only thus much, <hi>Let them grow together till the harvest, leſt in plucking up the tares, you pull up the wheat alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Parliament having ſate about as many weeks as the other had done years, though in that time (to give them their due) they had made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall laudable Acts, and of great utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and advantage to the people, <hi>viz.</hi> An Act for taking off the Engagement; for taking off Fines from Originall Writs and Declarations; for clearing of Publike Debts, and diſcovery of frauds and concealements due to the Commonwealth: as alſo an Act for Relief of Creditors, and poor Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which of all others, was of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er concernment to the Nation then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing they could do: Other Acts of leſſe moment they made alſo, which I ſhall forbear to mention. Yet in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things of no ſmall conſequence, there appeared ſuch conſuſion in their Councels, ſuch contrariety in their
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:151118:85"/>opinions, ſuch a diſſonaacy in their actings, and diſparity in their aims, that they ſeemed to be a meer monſter with many heads; inſomuch that it was not expected their power (as then it ſtood) would continue unto the time prefixt.</p>
            <p>For on the 10. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1653. the Parliament (having heard the Report of the Committee,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they thought it ſitting that Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners be ſent into all the Counties, and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to eject ſcandalous and unable Miniſters; and alſo be impowered to ſettle able Miniſters in all void places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ſuch as are or ſhall be approved for publike Preachers of the Goſpel, ſhall have and enjoy ſuch maintenance as is already ſetled by Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That upon hearing and conſidering what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath been offered to the Committee touching propriety in Tithes, of Incumbents, Rectors, Poſſeſſours of Donatives, or appropriate Tithes; It is the opinion of this Committee, That the ſaid perſons have a Legal propriety in Tithes</hi>) The Parliament, I ſay, having ſpent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall dayes in debate of this Report, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 10. put the firſt of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports to the Queſtion, viz. <hi>Whether the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:151118:86"/>Houſe doth agree with the firſt Clauſe of this Report?</hi> which was carryed in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</p>
            <p>Monday, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 12. ſomewhat early, the Houſe being ſate, a Gentleman ſtood up and moved,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the ſitting of this Parliament, as then conſtituted, would not be for the good of the Commonwealth; and that therefore it was requiſite to deliver up unto the Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> Cromwell <hi>the Powers which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This motion being ſeconded by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Members, the houſe roſe, &amp; the Speaker with many Members of the Houſe, departed and went to <hi>White-hall,</hi> where they (being the greater number of the Members ſitting in Parliament) did by a Writing under their hands,<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament diſſolved, <hi>Decem.</hi> 12. 1653.</note> reſign unto his Excellency their ſaid Powers; and Mr. Speaker, attended with the Members, did preſent the ſame to his Excellency accordingly.</p>
            <p>This was no ſooner done, but (after ſerious conſultation and debate about the emergent occaſions of the Land) the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> was (in the preſence of all the Judges and Juſtices of the ſeverall Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:151118:86"/>the Barons of the Exchequer, the Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> the Lord Major, and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London,</hi> with moſt of the chief Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army) ſworn Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of all the Iſlands and Territories thereunto belonging: ſeveral Articles by which he is to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the People, being then read to him, to the performance whereof, he took a ſolemne Oath in the preſence of them all; the ſumme whereof was,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he ſhould call a Parliament every three years. That the firſt ſhould be</hi> Sept. 3. 1654. <hi>That he ſhould not diſſolve it untill they had ſate five moneths. That whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Bill they ſhould paſſe, if he ſhould not ſign it in twentie dayes, that then it ſhould paſſe without him. That he ſhould have a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of ſelect Perſons to aſſiſt him, not under</hi> 13. <hi>nor above</hi> 21. <hi>That immediately after his death, the Councell ſhall chooſe another Protector before they riſe. That no Protector for the future ſhall be Generall of the Army. That the Protector ſhall have power to make Peace or Warre. That with the conſent of his Councell, he may make Lawes which ſhal
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:151118:87"/>be binding till the next Seſſion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe with many more particulars you may read at large in the <hi>Forme</hi> of <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after this he was proclaimed Lord Protector in the <hi>Palace-yard</hi> at <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> and by the Lord Major and Aldermen in their Scarlet Gowns at the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after his Highneſſe the Lord Protector was by the City invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Feaſt at <hi>Grocers-Hall,</hi> the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of whoſe reception was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
            <p>He came from <hi>Westminſter</hi> in a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot drawn with ſix Horſes, in gallant equipage; before him rode his Life-Guard, with moſt of his chief Officers, and ſome of his Councell; after them rode two Pages bareheaded in ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous apparell; after them about twelve Lackeys, with velvet Caps in gray Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries with ſilk and ſilver Fringe; then came his Highneſſe, as aforeſaid, in a Chariot, clad in a dark coloured Suit and Cloak, attended by many of the Nobility in their Coaches with ſix Horſes. At <hi>Temple-barre</hi> his Highneſs was
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:151118:87"/>met by the Lord Major and Aldermen, where the Recorder of <hi>London</hi> ſaluted him with a pithy and excellent Speech. His Highneſſe then came out of his Chariot, put on a riding Coat im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered with Gold Lace, and mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on horſeback, two or three of his horſes of State being there led by: which done, the Lord Major took the City-Sword, and carried it bareheaded from thence to <hi>Grocers-Hall,</hi> all the way whereof the ſeverall Companies in their Liveries ſate on both fides the way, in Rails ſet up on purpoſe, with Strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers ſticking up to diſtinguiſh each Company. After his Highneſſe had dined, and banquet was ended, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd upon the Lord Major the Honour of Knighthood.</p>
            <p>Which piece of magnificence had no ſooner been performed, but as a Remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra to that happy ſettlement, ſo long contended for by all good men, there conſpicuouſly appeared a moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean work of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">A plot diſcovered</note> a ſecret conſpiracy carryed on by the old reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe party on the behalf of <hi>Charles Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art,</hi> which being diſcovered <hi>Feb.</hi> 18. 1653. eleven of them were ſent cloſe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:151118:88"/>priſoners to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> where being retained a ſhort time, his Highneſſe clemency extended ſo far as to ſet them at liberty.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time as a ſure teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall of the peoples affection to his Highneſſe Government,<note place="margin">Addreſſes from all parts of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> there appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed addreſſes and congratulations from all parts of this Nation, <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> his Highneſſe likewiſe by way of Retaliation, made ſeverall good Acts, tending to the glory of God, and the good of the Common-wealth, more eſpecially that for the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of publick Preachers: But at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent leaving this let us look Northward, where, about this time, high were the expectations and hopes of the <hi>Scots,</hi> partly from the unſetled ſpirits of ſome male-contented perſons in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as alſo from the great promiſes that their King made to them, by his Agents, inſomuch that they doubted not but to have once more a fair trial of their quarrell in the field, and to that end having received ample Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from their King, they had ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly formed an Army of about four thouſand Horſe and Foot,<note place="margin">The Scots rally.</note> being head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:151118:88"/>by the Earl of <hi>Glencarne</hi> and <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more;</hi> but this bubble was ſoon broak by the vigilance of Collonel <hi>Morgan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Are rout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> who with about 1500 horſe and foot, <hi>Feb.</hi> 17. came to the <hi>Lough,</hi> where <hi>Glencarn</hi> and the reſt were at a Rendezvouze, and after a little diſpute, he totally routed their Army, having killed of them about 150. <hi>Glencarn</hi> himſelf hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſcaping with fortie horſe. But leaving <hi>Scotland,</hi> we preſent you with the main buſineſſe in agitation at this time, <hi>viz.</hi> The Dutch Peace,<note place="margin">The Dutch Peace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</note> to which end four Ambaſſadors from them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reſided here all laſt winter, and having well nigh-finiſhed their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in <hi>February</hi> two of them went over, the Lord <hi>Newport,</hi> and <hi>Youngſtall,</hi> for full power and ratification, and having returned and landed at the <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> Wharf, <hi>March</hi> 3. 1654. were hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably attended through the City, and the next day had audience of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, declaring their ful impowerment from their Superiors, for the ratifying of the Peace lately agreed on, deſiring a ſpeedy ceſſation of Arms on both ſides: This was the effect of what was by them delivered; and accordingly to
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:151118:89"/>the great joy of all the Reformed Churches, on the 5 of <hi>April</hi> following, the Articles of Peace betwixt both States were ſigned and ſealed on both fides, and ſhortly after proclaimed both in <hi>England,</hi> and in the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> The Dutch Ambaſſadors the day after the Peace proclaimed were nobly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and feaſted by the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector.</p>
            <p>As to the affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſtate of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </note> much can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid, more then ſome years paſt, ſaving that the Country more and more tends towards the center of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement through the great vigilance of the Lord Deputy and Councel there, who having through a great deal of difficultie gon through with the work of tranſplanting the <hi>Iriſh</hi> into the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Conaught,</hi> by means whereof the lives and eſtates of the Engliſh are throughly ſecured, and upon the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralty of that Country there appears a good face of health and quiet.</p>
            <p>Now whilſt <hi>Ireland</hi> was in this quiet ſtate, the old malignant Party, was hatching new broyls in the heart of England;<note place="margin">A ſecond Plotdiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</note> as appeared upon the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of a barbarous conſpiracy on the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:151118:89"/>20th. of <hi>May,</hi> 1654. undertaken by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perſons of ſeverall intereſts in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, their intent being by a villanous aſſaſſination to have turned the State in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to blood and confuſion: a piece of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo much the more to be deteſted in England, in regard the generous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Engliſh doth uſually abhor ſuch unmanly practiſes, ſo that they have very rarely been heard of amongſt us: divers were apprehended about it, and examined, as <hi>Gilbert Gerard</hi> Eſq; and <hi>John Gerard</hi> his brother, <hi>John Jones,</hi> an Apothecary, <hi>Thomas Tudor,</hi> with ſeverall others, who were all of them committed to the Tower, and ſhortly after a high Court of juſtice being erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe three were tryed in the firſt place, <hi>viz. John Gerard, Somerſet Fox,</hi> and <hi>Peter Vowel,</hi> who being found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were condemned to be hanged,<note place="margin">The plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</note> and it was accordingly performed on <hi>Peter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>owel; Gerard</hi> upon petition was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, and <hi>Somerſet Fox</hi> for his inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous and ſubmiſſive confeſſion his Highneſſe pardoned.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſame day that theſe Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſuffered, <hi>Don Pautalcon ſa</hi> brother to the Lord Ambaſſador of <hi>Portugal,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:151118:90"/>been Priſoner in <hi>Newgate</hi> a long time,<note place="margin">The <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors brother beheaded with <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard.</hi>
               </note> for a Ryot by him and others committed at the New <hi>Exchange,</hi> and having been lately brought to his triall at the upper Bench barre, was at firſt very peremptory, refuſing to be uncovered, or to plead; but at length he was told by an Interpreter that he ought to plead or to undergo the Law, which was to be preſſed to death, which having a while ſlighted, he at length pleaded not guilty, but being found guilty he was condemned to be hanged, but through the favour of the Court the ſentence was altered, to be beheaded; which was accordingly performed, on the 10. of <hi>July,</hi> on <hi>Tower-hill</hi> with <hi>Gerard:</hi> an exemplary piece of juſtice.</p>
            <p>Theſe Plots in <hi>England</hi> being thus nipt in the bud,<note place="margin">Middleton <hi>routed in</hi> Scotland.</note> did nothing diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Scotch malignants in the Highlands, but that they brought their deſigns to more maturity; for having got ſome addition of ſtrength by the landing of <hi>Middleton</hi> out of <hi>Holland</hi> as Generaliſſimo, they ſoon got the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of terming themſelves an Army; but as a means for the diſpelling of that Scotch miſt, <hi>Monk</hi> was ſent into
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:151118:90"/>the North as Generall, where having attended their motions, and ſate hard upon their skirts ſome certain time, on the 21 of <hi>July,</hi> 1654. he engaged them by <hi>Loughgery,</hi> and after ſome ſmall reſiſtance, totally routed them and all their hopes together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Septemb.</hi> 3. 1654.<note place="margin">Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment met <hi>Sep.</hi> 3.</note> According to Writs formerly iſſued out, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament met at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Sermon preached by Mr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> they repaired to the Parliament Houſe, and having choſen <hi>William Lenthall</hi> their Speaker, they then began to queſtion the lawfulneſſe of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that called them thither, inſomuch that his Highneſſe conſidering the growing evils that were like to afflict the Nation in caſe of new changes, and revolutions, appointed a Teſt or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognition of the Government, which was to be ſigned by them before ever they entred the houſe again, which being accordingly ſigned by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty of them, they took their places again, and having ſate full five moneths, and in that time done nothing of that main work which they were called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for, which was by their unity
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:151118:91"/>to cement the hearts of the people of this Nation together, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, by their ſeverall diviſions and animoſities (much like to <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes faſtened together at the tails) they feed the Common people with hopes that they ſhould once more have a day of it, which till their ſitting they deſpaired of; all which his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe conſidering of, on the 22 of <hi>Jan.</hi> actually diſſolved them:<note place="margin">Diſſolved <hi>Jan.</hi> 22.</note> and ful time it was, for before their diſſolution, to wit on the 10 of <hi>January,</hi> 1655. a new conſpiracy was detected againſt his Highneſſe, and the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the venom and contagion of which had ſpread it ſelf into moſt parts of this Nation, Sir <hi>Henry Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Sir <hi>John Packington,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A third Plot diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>covered.</note> with ſeverall other were apprehended about it; on the <hi>Lilburnian</hi> account was apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their grand ſtickler Major <hi>Wildman,</hi> as he was dictating to another a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet bearing this title, A Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſetting forth the grounds and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our taking Arms againſt <hi>Oliver Cromwell:</hi> Nay ſo generall was this deſign, that although very much of it was diſcovered, yet their confidence was
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:151118:91"/>ſo great, that they feared not but to carry it on without their friends al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in priſon about it, and to that end upon the 13. of <hi>March</hi> divtrs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons came poſt from <hi>Salisbury,</hi> giving an account of the riſing of a party of Cavaliers in thoſe parts, who came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Salisbury</hi> on the Lords day at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, about 200 in a body, the aſſizes being there held by the Lord chief Juſtice Rolls, and Judge <hi>Nicolas,</hi> where having clapt guards to all the Innes of the Town, their inſolence tranſported them ſo farre, as to take away the Judges commiſſions, and having ſeiſed on all their horſes left them, and marcht away towards <hi>Poole,</hi> being headed by one <hi>Wagſtaffe, Penruddock,</hi> and <hi>Jones,</hi> Captains in the late Kings Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: and further to ſhew the condition of this frantick generation, at the ſame time another party of them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured the ſurprizall of the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Shrewslu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</hi>
               </note> but being timely diſcovered, were prevented.</p>
            <p>News was likewiſe brought of a freſh party riſen in <hi>Mount Gomeryſhire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A party riſen in <hi>Mountgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery-ſhire.</hi>
               </note> where they were encreaſed to the number of 800, acting both publickly and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently.</p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:151118:92"/>
            <p>A meſſenger came alſo out of <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham-ſhire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And in <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham-ſhire.</hi>
               </note> which brought informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a party of 500 Horſe that were gotten together in the Forreſt of <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> in that County, having a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage laden with Arms, with them; and being conſulting in a by Inne, how to manage their buſineſſe, a ſodain fear taking them, they cryed out they were betrayed, and ſo diſperſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Letters came likewiſe from Coll.<note place="margin">And in <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lilburn</hi> out of the North certifying that in <hi>Northumberland</hi> there was another party up, but they being betraid by their own fears, and jealouſies diſperſt again of themſelves.</p>
            <p>And for a finall concluſion of all theſe riſings,<note place="margin">And in <hi>York-ſhire.</hi>
               </note> there was likewiſe an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in <hi>York-ſhire</hi> to form a party, many being met for that purpoſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Heſham</hi> Moor, with an intent to ſeiſe <hi>York</hi> for <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> they had two Carts full of Armes and Ammunition with them, and divers of the Gentry, amongſt whom was Sir <hi>Henry Slaigsby,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Malleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer;</hi> but they likewiſe diſperſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving no ſuch appearance as they
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:151118:92"/>expected. Sir <hi>Henry Slaigsby</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; Sir <hi>Richard Malleverer</hi> eſcaped. The like ſucceſſe of theſe unfortunate men you may expect in this following relation.</p>
            <p>On the 16 of <hi>March</hi> 1655 came Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from Captain <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nton Crook,</hi> ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the total defeat of the Cavaliers under the command of <hi>Wagſtaffe, Jones, Penruddock,</hi> and <hi>Groves,</hi> for having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued them out of <hi>Wilt-ſhire</hi> into <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wagſtaffe <hi>&amp;</hi> Penrudock <hi>routed.</hi>
               </note> he having only his own Troop fell into their quarters, in a Town called <hi>South Molton,</hi> where after four hours diſpute with them, he took ſome 60 priſoners, and neer 140 Horſe and Arms; <hi>Wagſtaffe</hi> eſcaped, <hi>Jones Penrud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock</hi> and <hi>Groves</hi> he took, where having delivered them over to the high Sheriff of the County, they were committed to <hi>Exon</hi> Gaol, where having a ſhort time reamained, a commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Are tryed condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted.</note> was iſſued forth for the triall of the Weſtern Cavaliers at <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> where 30 were convicted, and 14 condemned, <hi>Penrudock</hi> and <hi>Groves</hi> were two of them for Treaſon, in levying warre: and on the 3 of <hi>May,</hi> executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was done upon three of them, by
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:151118:93"/>name, <hi>Lacas, Thorp,</hi> and <hi>Kenſey; Lacas</hi> was beheaded, the other two were hanged. News came likewiſe from <hi>Exeter,</hi> giving information, that on the 9 of <hi>May,</hi> execution was done there upon 14 of the condemned perſons, on the 9 of <hi>May, Penruddock</hi> and <hi>Groves</hi> had ſo much favour ſhewed them as to be beheaded: the greateſt part of them were reprieved (whereof <hi>Jones</hi> was one) by order of his Highneſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jones</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preived.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And further for the ſecuring of the peace of the Commonwealth it was ordered that divers perſons priſoners in the Tower,<note place="margin">Divers Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers ſent to Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> who were in the laſt yeers conſpiracy againſt his Highneſſe perſon, and moſt of thoſe in the Gaols of the Weſt, who were in the late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Inſurrection, ſhould be ſent away to forreign Plantations.</p>
            <p>Now on the other hand,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cople<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> knight<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed.</note> as a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all remark of true valour, on the 1 of <hi>June,</hi> Mr. <hi>Copleſton</hi> high Sheriffe of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire,</hi> was Knighted by his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for the good ſervice he did in his Country, at the time of the late In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, his Highneſſe likewiſe gave him the Sword he Knighted him with, as a further addition of honour.</p>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:151118:93"/>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 2. 1655.<note place="margin">An Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador from <hi>Spain</hi>
               </note> The Marqueſſe of <hi>Loyd,</hi> extraordinary Ambaſſador from his Majeſty of <hi>Spain,</hi> arrived at <hi>Dover,</hi> and ſo coming to <hi>Greenwitch,</hi> was there attended by the Maſter of the Ceremonies, and divers Gentlemen of his Highneſſe, from thence by water to <hi>Tower-wharf,</hi> where he was met and conducted thence with a ſtately train of Coaches through the City to <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> there to receive the uſuall enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, for three dayes, after which his Excellency removed to <hi>Dorſet</hi> houſe, in <hi>Salisbury</hi> Court, and on the 8 of <hi>May,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hath Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and takes his leave.</note> his Highneſſe gave publike audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Lord Ambaſſador in the banqueting houſe, and having had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall other audiences, and nothing concluded, on the 12 of <hi>June</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he tooke his leave of his Highneſs, where many complements paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them at the interview.</p>
            <p>The peace (as you have heard before) being lately concluded with the Dutch,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pen</hi>'s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</note> and to the intent that the bulwarks of this Commonwealth ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume away to no advantage, it was therefore reſolved for the equipring out of a Fleet, which having been at
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:151118:94"/>laſt brought to perfection, on the 27. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1654. they ſet ſail from <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> under the command of Generall <hi>Pen,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enables,</hi> upon an unknown expedition, but to cleare doubts, in part conceiving their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: on the 1 of <hi>May,</hi> 1655. came Letters from Generall <hi>Pen,</hi> dated at the <hi>Barbadoes, March</hi> 19. certifying the good condition of the whole Fleet,<note place="margin">Is at <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does.</hi>
               </note> having arrived there on the 28 of <hi>January</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and there he ſeiſed on 18 Dutch Merchant men, who traded there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to an Act of the long Parliament: as alſo by later Letters from them it appeared that they ſet ſaile from <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badoes</hi> the 30 of <hi>March,</hi> and ſailed for <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> where after their landing, having received ſome ſmall check (ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying that excellent ſaying, <hi>Man propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth but God diſpoſeth</hi>) they re-embarqued for the Iſland of <hi>Jamaica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>At</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maica.</note> where they arrived the 10 of <hi>May</hi> following, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in full poſſeſſion of it, after ſome ſmall reſiſtance by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and receiving it as an earneſt peny of thoſe great things that ſhall be done by the Engliſh Nation in Gods good time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the perfidious Nation of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:151118:94"/>
            <p>Now ſomewhat to raiſe the ſpirits of the Engliſh again, whom any ill fortune dejects, take an account of the wonderfull ſucceſs it pleaſed God to beſtow upon Generall <hi>Blake,</hi> againſt the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Pirates of <hi>Tunis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Generall <hi>Blakes</hi> ſucceſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Turks.</hi>
               </note> where he having on the 18 of <hi>April,</hi> 1655. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of the Dye of that place ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for ſome Ships which they had taken, as alſo the Captives of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but being denyed either of them, and withall they giving ſome provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king terms, as in theſe and ſuch like words. Theſe are our Caſtles of the <hi>Galletta,</hi> and the Ships and Caſtles of <hi>Porto Ferino,</hi> do what you can, do not think to fear us with the ſhew of your Fleet. The Generall ſeeing himſelf ſo ſlighted, called a Councell of War, where after the ſeeking of counſell of the Lord to direct them in that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they reſolved to burn thoſe Ships that lay in <hi>Porto Ferino,</hi> if it were poſſible, being nine in number, which they thus effected: the Admiral, Vice-Admiral, and Rear-Admiral lay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Musket ſhot of their Caſtle, which had 20 Guns in it, playing continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally both upon it and their Forts, the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:151118:95"/>wind likewiſe favouring, it pleaſed God to put ſuch courage into the Engliſh,<note place="margin">Their 9 Ships ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> that in four hours time all their nine Ships were burnt down to the water by the Engliſh Boats; in which nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervice, there were loſt in the whole Fleet but 25 men, and 48 woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which mercy was the more ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, conſidering that there was 120 Guns planted on the ſhore, and in the Caſtle againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> 12,<note place="margin">A fourth plot ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</note> Upon ſuſpicion of a new Plot there was committed to the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the Lord <hi>Willowby</hi> of <hi>Parham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> the Lord <hi>Newport,</hi> Mr. <hi>Newport,</hi> with others, of which more in it's due place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Major <hi>Sedgewick</hi> ſet ſail.</note> Advice was brought that Major <hi>Sedgewick</hi> with a gallant ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Ships, 12 in number, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Humphreys</hi> with his Regiment of Souldiers, deſigned for the aſſiſtance of our Generals in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, did ſet ſail out of <hi>Dover</hi> Road the 2 of <hi>July:</hi> the Lord proſper them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt</hi> 31.<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>Pen</hi> arrived from <hi>Weſt-Indies.</hi>
               </note> Generall <hi>Pen</hi> arrived at the <hi>Spithead,</hi> neer <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> from <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maica,</hi> with part of the Fleet, having left a conſiderable Squadron behind
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:151118:95"/>him in thoſe ſeas. He came from thence the 25 of <hi>June,</hi> and being come as far as the <hi>Havana</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Cuba,</hi> the Ship <hi>Baiagon</hi> fell on fire, by negligence, and ſo periſhed in the ſea, blowing up many of her men that were in her. The Army left at <hi>Jamaica</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Collonel <hi>Forteſcue,</hi> the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Shps, by a truly valiant man, Vice-Admirall <hi>Goadſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe on the 9 of <hi>September</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing arrived Generall <hi>Venables</hi> in the <hi>Maſton More</hi> Frigot,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nables</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> very weak, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been at deaths dore, ſo that in all probability nothing but change of air would have ſaved his life.</p>
            <p>Now here by the way, take a relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Preſident ſeldome heard of, the reſignation of the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Queen of <hi>Swedens</hi> reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> who from a powerfull Princeſſe put her ſelf into the condition of a Lady Arrant; now whilſt ſhe was project<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the buſineſſe, theſe propoſitions ſhe made to the Prince her Succeſſor.</p>
            <p n="1">1. She will retain the beſt part of the Kingdome, and the cuſtome to her ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She will be no ſubject, but free of her ſelf without controul.</p>
            <pb n="182" facs="tcp:151118:96"/>
            <p n="3">3. She will travell whither ſhe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
            <p>The Prince replyed,
<list>
                  <item>1. That he would not be a King without a Kingdome.</item>
                  <item>2. He will have no Rivall more then ſhe a Superior.</item>
                  <item>3. He will not hazard himſelf about her deſigns abroad.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But how theſe differences in theſe propoſals were compoſed I know not. But in a ſhort time ſhe wholly reſigned all, leaving her ſelf only the bare title of the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> having ever ſince rambled up and down according as her wild fancy led her: and for the to tall finiſhing of the comick Scene, ſhe hath at length reſigned up her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and is received into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which City having at laſt arrived to, I there leave her: and return to the happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the Lord <hi>Whitlock,</hi> who having gone Ambaſſador into <hi>Sweden,</hi> and there reſided about eight moneths, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving finiſhed his affairs, in concluding a firm peace with that Crown, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>London</hi> in <hi>February,</hi> 1654.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sept.</hi> 5. It was confirmed from <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onne,</hi>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:151118:96"/>and <hi>Sant Sabaſtian,</hi> that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had made a ſeiſure of the perſons and goods of the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octob.</hi> 24.<note place="margin">A Peace with <hi>France</hi> concluded.</note> The Articles of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> were ſigned by the Commiſſioners impowered by ſpeciall Commiſſion for that purpoſe from his Highneſſe the Lord Protector on the one part, and on the other part, by his Excellency the Lord Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of <hi>France:</hi> and on the 28 of <hi>Novemb.</hi> Publication was made of the treaty of Peace, firſt in the Court of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> by the ſound of Trumpet, and the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds attending in their formality: Afterwards in the Palace-yard at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and in all the uſuall places throughout the City of <hi>London.</hi> The like was by appointment to be done the ſame day at <hi>Paris,</hi> all ceremonies of publick rejoicing were expreſſed by the Family of the Lord Ambaſſador of <hi>France,</hi> as alſo by all the generality of the people of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Reader have I brought my Story from the end of one Monarchy to the third year of the Government
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:151118:97"/>of his Highneſſe: under which (if is pleaſe the wiſe Diſpoſer of all things, as well as perſons, to grant us Peace, both at home and abroad) both thou and I may live to ſee happy dayes. And if it ſhall pleaſe God to ſpin out the thred of my life to ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable length, I ſhall afford the world ſome other things of the like nature: but if not, I am content to <hi>acquieſce</hi> in the good will of him that dwelt in the Buſh, and ſo Farewell.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151118:97"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
